<CHAPTER NUMBER="3"><TL-CHAP VL="BG" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Единна реакция на ЕС на неоправданите търговски мерки на САЩ и възможностите за ЕС за търговия в световен мащаб (разискване)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="ES" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Respuesta unificada de la Unión a las injustificadas medidas comerciales de los Estados Unidos y oportunidades comerciales a escala mundial para la Unión (debate)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="CS" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Jednotná reakce EU na neodůvodněná obchodní opatření USA a celosvětové obchodní příležitosti pro EU (rozprava)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="DA" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">En samlet reaktion fra EU&apos;s side på uberettigede amerikanske handelsforanstaltninger og EU&apos;s globale handelsmuligheder (forhandling)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="DE" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Einheitliche Reaktion der EU auf die ungerechtfertigten US-Handelsmaßnahmen und globale Handelsmöglichkeiten für die EU (Aussprache)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="ET" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">ELi ühtne vastus USA põhjendamatutele kaubandusmeetmetele ning ELi ülemaailmsed kaubandusvõimalused (arutelu)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="EL" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Μια ενιαία αντίδραση της ΕΕ στα αδικαιολόγητα εμπορικά μέτρα των ΗΠΑ και ευκαιρίες παγκόσμιου εμπορίου για την ΕΕ (συζήτηση)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="EN" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">A unified EU response to unjustified US trade measures and global trade opportunities for the EU (debate)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="FR" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Une réponse unifiée de l&apos;Union aux mesures commerciales injustifiées des États-Unis et les débouchés commerciaux à l&apos;échelle mondiale pour l&apos;Union (débat)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="GA" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Freagairt aontaithe ón Aontas ar bhearta trádála gan údar na Stát Aontaithe, agus deiseanna trádála domhanda don Eoraip (díospóireacht)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="HR" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Jedinstveni odgovor EU-a na neopravdane trgovinske mjere SAD-a te globalne trgovinske mogućnosti za EU (rasprava)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="IT" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Una risposta unificata alle misure commerciali ingiustificate degli Stati uniti e opportunità commerciali europee a livello globale (discussione)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="LV" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Vienota ES reaģēšana uz nepamatotajiem ASV tirdzniecības pasākumiem un ES globālās tirdzniecības iespējas (debates)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="LT" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Vieningas ES atsakas į nepagrįstas JAV prekybos priemones ir pasaulinės prekybos galimybės Europos Sąjungai (diskusijos)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="HU" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Egységes uniós válasz az USA indokolatlan kereskedelmi intézkedéseire és globális kereskedelmi lehetőségek az Unió számára (vita)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="MT" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Rispons unifikat tal-UE għall-miżuri kummerċjali inġustifikati tal-Istati Uniti u opportunitajiet kummerċjali globali għall-UE (dibattitu)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="NL" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Een gezamenlijke reactie van de EU op ongerechtvaardigde handelsmaatregelen van de VS en mondiale handelsmogelijkheden voor de EU (debat)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="PL" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Jednolita reakcja UE na nieuzasadnione amerykańskie środki handlowe oraz globalne możliwości handlowe dla UE (debata)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="PT" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Uma resposta unificada da UE a medidas comerciais injustificadas por parte dos EUA e oportunidades de comércio para a UE a nível mundial (debate)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="RO" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Un răspuns unitar al UE la măsurile comerciale nejustificate ale SUA și oportunități comerciale la nivel mondial pentru UE (dezbatere)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="SK" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Jednotná reakcia EÚ na neodôvodnené obchodné opatrenia USA a globálne obchodné príležitosti pre EÚ (rozprava)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="SL" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Enoten odziv EU na neupravičene trgovinske ukrepe ZDA in priložnosti EU na področju svetovne trgovine (razprava)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="FI" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">EU:n yhtenäinen vastaus Yhdysvaltojen perusteettomiin kauppatoimenpiteisiin ja maailmankaupan EU:lle tarjoamat mahdollisuudet (keskustelu)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="SV" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07">Ett enhetligt svar från EU på obefogade amerikanska handelsåtgärder samt globala handelsmöjligheter för EU (debatt)</TL-CHAP><NUMERO VL="SK" INDEX="2-0008-0000" ACT="2017023813486" PRE="2017023813484" SUIV="2017023813487" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:02:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:03:08"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Predsedajúci " PP="NULL" LG="SK" MEPID="197770" CODICT="197770"><LG>SK</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Predsedajúci .</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Ďalším bodom programu je vyhlásenie Rady a Komisie: Jednotná reakcia Európskej únie na neodôvodnené obchodné opatrenia USA a globálne obchodné príležitosti pre Európsku úniu (<a href="#reds:DirContProc/RSP-2025-2657" data-rel="reds" redmap-uri="/reds:DirContProc/RSP-2025-2657">2025/2657(RSP)</a>).</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0009-0000" ACT="2017023813487" PRE="2017023813486" SUIV="2017023813489" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:03:08" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:09:20"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Adam | Szłapka" PP="NULL" LG="EN" MEPID="0" CODICT="264609" SPEAKER_TYPE="président en exercice du Conseil"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Adam Szłapka, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">President-in-Office of the Council</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Mr President, honourable Members, Commissioner, the EU-US trade and investment partnership is the most valuable in the world. I am convinced that we have a shared interest in protecting this mutually beneficial partnership and working together on common challenges.</PARA><PARA>In this context, we deeply regret the recent increases of US tariffs applied on a very broad range of EU goods. We think that the imposition of additional tariffs, both universal and sectoral ones, is unjustified and arbitrary. These tariffs are damaging for prosperity. They negatively impact economic growth, foremost in the US but also globally, as confirmed by the IMF and WTO in their latest forecasts. Tariffs are taxes paid by businesses and ultimately by consumers. They will raise the cost of imports, disrupt supply chains and force companies to either absorb the cost or pass them on through higher prices, building up inflation.</PARA><PARA>We welcome the 90-day suspension of a portion of the recently imposed US universal tariffs. At the same time, we are deeply concerned by many tariff increases remaining in place and possible new tariffs. More importantly, we are very concerned by the uncertainty that the US Administration announcements brought to the global economy. We understand that the US seeks to strengthen the resilience of its domestic industrial base and to enhance its economic security, but we believe that the announced tariffs are not the right way to achieve these goals.</PARA><PARA>On behalf of the Council, I can assure you that we are united in our readiness to engage in a constructive dialogue with the US. Our priority is clearly to agree on a solution that is balanced and mutually beneficial, and that brings about more predictable trade and investment conditions. We believe that there is sufficient scope for delivering such a solution, but it is clear that significant joint efforts will still be needed to get there.</PARA><PARA>We welcome recent concrete steps made by the Commission in the form of an offer of negotiations in selected areas. This step has full backing from the Council. As a clear sign of our good faith and our restraint, we have temporarily suspended the first set of countermeasures. It is also a sign of us not wishing to add to the already an unprecedented levels of economic uncertainty. But let me be clear: we will defend our legitimate interests and rights if we have to, and we will do so in a united, targeted and measured manner.</PARA><PARA>There is a broad agreement in the Council on the need to work on possible further countermeasures, which would complement those already adopted. Our countermeasures can be fully reversed at any time if a negotiated solution is found. If, however, negotiation failed to deliver the desired outcome, we will consider taking further steps, keeping all options on the table, including a WTO complaint. We are working closely with the Commission. We are carefully assessing not only the effects of new US tariffs on EU exports, but also monitoring any unwanted indirect effects. We simply cannot absorb global overcapacity, we cannot accept dumping on our markets.</PARA><PARA>Mr President, honourable Members, Commissioner, in these challenging times, we remain committed to the rules-based international order, as we continue to believe in an open and predictable global trading system that benefits all partners. We are engaging with our international partners both through multilateral fora as well as bilaterally. That is why the issue of possible trade diversion is firmly on our radar screen. In the Council, there is a broad agreement on the importance of deepening our existing partnerships around the world, as well as sealing new win-win deals.</PARA><PARA>Finally, I want to underline that in times of growing uncertainty, the single market stands as a vital source of stability and resilience. The new situation we are facing gives an additional sense of urgency in implementing the new European competitiveness deal. We will therefore be stepping up our work in the Council towards lifting the remaining barriers to the proper functioning of our single market and boosting its potential.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0010-0000" ACT="2017023813489" PRE="2017023813487" SUIV="2017023813491" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:09:25" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:22:12"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Maroš | Šefčovič" PP="NULL" LG="EN" MEPID="0" CODICT="99424" SPEAKER_TYPE="membre de la Commission"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Maroš Šefčovič, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">Member of the Commission</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Mr President, honourable Members, dear Minister, dear Andre, first and foremost, I would like to appreciate that we have this very timely debate this morning, because it would allow us to have a deep look at the current state of our relationship between the European Union and the United States of America in the field of bilateral trade and economic cooperation.</PARA><PARA>As was already highlighted by the Minister, we have built, together with the United States, over the years the largest bilateral and investment relationship in the world. Today, the European Union is by far the most important economic partner of the United States. Our trade in goods and services has doubled over the last decade, surpassing EUR 1.7 trillion in 2023, with EUR 851 billion of trade in goods and EUR 746 billion of trade in services. And for us, likewise, the US is our biggest trading partner. Our business communities have invested strongly on both sides. Total bilateral investment stocks reached EUR 5.3 trillion in 2022. Direct EU investment in the US is worth of EUR 2.7 trillion, making the EU companies the largest foreign investor in the United States of America.</PARA><PARA>On top of it, I think it is very important to underline that European companies, EU firms directly employ 3.4 million people in the US, with millions more American workers, farmers and ranchers benefiting indirectly. Trade and investment between the European Union and the United States are therefore key building blocks of our shared prosperity, technology and research prowess, as well as remaining fundamental to our economic security. So it is evident that we have a mutual interest in nurturing and further developing our economic links and in making our partnership and relationship stronger.</PARA><PARA>But as you know very well, honourable Members, our trade relations are currently facing strong headwinds. The US has unilaterally increased its import duties on EU goods in a significant manner. These import taxes are unjustified and cause economic harm on both sides of the Atlantic. They disrupt supply chains and affect global markets. They hurt EU and US companies, workers and farmers. They create uncertainty for transatlantic investment. They raise prices for consumers and businesses and increase inflation in the US.</PARA><PARA>The US has temporarily decreased its universal additional tariffs from 20 % to 10 %. In response, we have shown significant goodwill by pausing our rebalancing measures on the steel and aluminium tariffs for 90 days. With this pause, we want to give space for negotiations. However, US tariffs still cover EUR 380 billion‑worth of EU exports to the US, corresponding to 70 % of our total exports, at rates between 10 % to 25 %. In addition, more US tariff actions could well be on their way, even though the US has acknowledged that the EU poses no problem and in fact shares many common challenges.</PARA><PARA>On top of the ongoing investigation on lumber, the US has recently launched new Section 232 investigations based on national security grounds on: pharmaceutical products and pharmaceutical ingredients; semiconductors, including semiconductor manufacturing equipment; critical minerals, also covering processed critical minerals and the derivative products; and, most recently, on tracks and track parts. This makes in total six additional ongoing investigations.</PARA><PARA>If all these investigations lead to unjustified harmful tariffs, then another EUR 170 billion of EU exports to the US would be impacted. This means that in total around EUR 549 billion of EU exports to the US, meaning 97 % of the total would be subject to tariffs. In the terms of duties collected, this will be massive. In 2024, the US collected around EUR 7 billion in duties on EU exports. The projection is that the US might now collect as much as EUR 100 billion if the ongoing investigations result in tariffs. And, as you know, just yesterday we learnt about a new possible 100 % tariff on non‑US film production. So I believe that you would agree with me that the situation as such is not acceptable and we cannot afford to stay idle. And this brings me to our response.</PARA><PARA>Honourable Members, we are not facing these headwinds on autopilot. As you know, President von der Leyen has entrusted me to engage with the US administration to try and find fair and mutually beneficial negotiated solutions and return to a constructive trade relationship. I am in constant contact with my US interlocutors for this purpose. In order to get these negotiations up and running, we have been scoping out the possibility to reduce barriers, not raise them, including by: proposing to agree on zero‑for‑zero tariffs for all industrial goods, including in strategic industrial sectors such as cars and car parts; jointly addressing global overcapacity in strategic industrial sectors such as steel and aluminium; jointly increasing the resilience of EU and US supply chains in sectors such as semiconductors and pharmaceuticals; and securing a return to barrier‑free transatlantic trade and reviving our cooperation.</PARA><PARA>So the EU has made clear that we are ready to discuss and we are ready to find mutually beneficial solutions respecting our interests and regulatory autonomy. We now need the US to show its readiness to make progress towards a fair and balanced solution. And I have already shared the approach with my US counterparts as a basis for further engagement. We are fully engaged in discussion with the US, as a negotiated solution remains our clear and preferred outcome.</PARA><PARA>But if our talks with the US do not yield the necessary result, we will be ready for alternatives, with the aim of restoring a level playing field. Therefore, we are also using the 90‑day pause to continue our preparation for further rebalancing measures to counter the multitude of additional US tariffs on EU exports and ensure a level playing field in the longer term. And here I would like to underline that all options remain on the table. We are also preparing for litigation to preserve and reinforce the multilateral rules‑based trading system. At the same time, we are monitoring possible risks of trade diversion, by way of a Dedicated Import Surveillance Task Force, where the aim is to protect the EU market from possible surges of imports from other countries that are also hit by US tariffs and which seek alternative markets. The first results of this work are anticipated in mid‑May.</PARA><PARA>The Commission stands ready, if necessary, to use all available tools in our trade defence instrument toolbox in a rapid manner to protect the EU single market, EU producers and EU consumers. We will also, honourable Members, continue diversifying our trade and investment ties with partners around the globe. This includes making the most of our extensive network of trade agreements with 76 countries across the globe, covering almost half of our trade, and doubling down on our efforts to finalise ongoing negotiations. Here, we know that countries around the world are looking at the EU as a trusted, reliable and predictable trading partner. In the current global environment, it is in everyone&apos;s interest to expand their network and strengthen their supply routes. For us, it is nothing less than a prerequisite for our competitiveness and our economic security that we find new markets for our exporters and new sources of imports, and it also helps double down on rules‑based trade, while we continue to push for proper multilateral governance with the WTO at its core.</PARA><PARA>The US represents 13 % of global trade. It&apos;s a lot, but we must not forget about the remaining 87 %. And, therefore, work continues internally towards the adoption of signature of agreements with Mercosur and Mexico. These are perfect examples of deals we have made that can deliver hugely on our bid for diversification, to open new markets and further important geopolitical relations, while also securing key commitments on issues of climate change and sustainability. They offer significant opportunities for EU businesses and high potential for EU consumers. There is still work to be done to get them over the line. However, I count on the support of this House to ensure successful outcomes for the benefit of all.</PARA><PARA>To conclude, Mr President, I also would like to inform the honourable Members that we are accelerating dramatically our ongoing negotiations with: India – we had very successful meetings just last week; Indonesia, where I had the important VTC yesterday; Philippines; Thailand; and Malaysia. As you know, we launched the free trade agreement talks with the United Arab Emirates, something which I believe could serve as a strong catalyst to advance our cooperation with the Gulf Cooperation Council countries with whom we are also negotiating strategic partnership agreements.</PARA><PARA>So while we are pushing our FTA agenda forward, we are also making use of other, more flexible forms of engagement tailor‑made to our own needs and those of our respective partners, covering specific sectors and deepening our bilateral relations.</PARA><PARA>Let me just conclude by highlighting that we are working very closely with Angola in implementing the Sustainable Investment Facilitation Agreement, which entered into force in 2024. And we are working closely with our partners on critical raw materials, but also on the digital trade agreements reached with South Africa earlier this year, and with Singapore, which I will be signing there on behalf of the EU this week. We are working very closely with South Africa also to advance our Clean Trade and Investment Partnership to strengthen our clean supply chains, which we hope to conclude by the end of 2025.</PARA><PARA>My last, last point would be an appeal to all of us, and I would like to thank the Polish Presidency for excellent cooperation on making sure that our unity is unshakeable, that we act as one if it comes to these very important trade negotiations, because this is as vital as ever. And I would say that this is the time to act in unequivocal terms for the EU&apos;s interest and towards our goal of maintaining a strong and competitive economy as well as cohesive society.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0011-0000" ACT="2017023813491" PRE="2017023813489" SUIV="2017023813493" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:22:26" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:24:53"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Jörgen | Warborn" PP="PPE" LG="EN" MEPID="197405" CODICT="197405" SPEAKER_TYPE="au nom du groupe"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Jörgen Warborn, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">on behalf of the PPE Group</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Mr President, Minister, Commissioner, colleagues, we find ourselves at a historic crossroads, not just in terms of economic policy, but also in the broader context of global geopolitics. Trade tension, of course, is nothing new. But today, in an era of deep globalisation and tightly interlinked supply chains, the consequences are more far-reaching than ever. We have seen this clearly in the past months, when Trump&apos;s erratic trade measures triggered volatility across financial markets.</PARA><PARA>The EU&apos;s response, especially in the face of the unjustified trade measures from a long-standing ally, will be remembered. Our approach must strike a careful balance, preserving the principle of trust, respect and transatlantic cooperation, while also shielding European citizens and industries from economic harm. I therefore call on the Commission to act decisively within their 90-day retaliatory pause. The current pause from the Trump administration is de facto a 25 % tariff on EU steel, aluminium and automobiles and a 10 % tariff on almost all other goods.</PARA><PARA>The Commission&apos;s decision to hold off on immediate retaliation is wise; de-escalation creates a space for dialogue. But let us be clear: inaction cannot become our policy. Within these 90 days, we must prepare a strong and measured and unified response. At the same time, we must do three things to strategically position Europe: strengthen the single market, negotiate and ratify more free trade agreements, not least Mercosur and the one with Mexico, and reassert leadership within WTO, because we need the rules-based international system when there is unpredictability in the world.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="ES" INDEX="2-0012-0000" ACT="2017023813493" PRE="2017023813491" SUIV="2017023813495" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:25:04" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:29:07"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Iratxe | García Pérez" PP="S-D" LG="ES" MEPID="28298" CODICT="28298" SPEAKER_TYPE="au nom du groupe"><LG>ES</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Iratxe García Pérez, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">en nombre del Grupo S&amp;D</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Señor presidente, querido comisario Šefčovič, Donald Trump y su visión del mundo son una amenaza directa no solo para el comercio internacional, sino también para los valores que sustentan nuestras democracias. Su guerra comercial contra la Unión Europea, con aranceles injustificados, amenazas a nuestras industrias y chantajes permanentes, es la manifestación más evidente de un nacionalismo económico autoritario que desprecia el derecho internacional y la cooperación entre iguales.</PARA><PARA>Trump y sus socios de extrema derecha —dentro y fuera de la Unión Europea— no creen en un mundo ordenado por normas, sino en la ley del más fuerte. Frente a su embestida, no podemos ni debemos titubear. Estamos aquí para defender con firmeza el modelo europeo, un modelo basado en la justicia social, en el Estado del bienestar y en una economía que pone en el centro a las personas.</PARA><PARA>La Unión Europea debe responder con contundencia. Nuestra respuesta debe desplegarse en varios frentes: la protección de nuestros trabajadores, consumidores y empresas; la defensa del orden internacional basado en reglas, con una Organización Mundial del Comercio fuerte y reformada; y la negociación frente a Trump desde una posición de firmeza, sin ceder a ningún tipo de chantaje.</PARA><PARA>Tenemos las herramientas, pero debemos usarlas cuando sea necesario si esta amenaza continúa. Debemos adoptar sanciones y gravámenes a las grandes tecnológicas que incumplen nuestras normas y excluir a las empresas de los Estados Unidos de la contratación pública europea si continúan esta amenaza y este chantaje. Al mismo tiempo, debemos reforzar el mercado interior, impulsar la demanda interna y apoyar con un plan de ayudas directas a la industria y a las regiones más afectadas por esta guerra comercial.</PARA><PARA>No olvidemos que el mundo es más grande que Trump. El 80 % de nuestras exportaciones se dirigen a otros mercados. Fortalezcamos los acuerdos con Canadá, Japón y México. Avancemos en Mercosur, India y con nuestros socios del África subsahariana. Diversificamos nuestra cadena de valor y hagamos de la Unión Europea una potencia líder a nivel mundial en comercio justo y sostenible.</PARA><PARA>Pero hay una cuestión que es fundamental, y es que hay elementos que no son negociables: el Estado de Derecho no es negociable. La legislación europea no es negociable, porque somos un modelo único en el mundo. Eso nos ha hecho diferentes. Eso nos ha hecho fuertes. Y no podemos aceptar chantajes que vayan permitiendo que Europa cambie y modifique la legislación en aquello que tanto hemos avanzado: en el Estado del bienestar, en materia de igualdad, en materia también de cuestiones de sostenibilidad.</PARA><PARA>La Unión Europea no puede ser rehén de cálculos electorales ni de tibiezas políticas. El reto al que nos enfrentamos es existencial. Se trata de decidir si queremos ser un actor global fuerte, soberano, con voz propia o si nos resignamos a ser meros espectadores sometidos a los caprichos de un demagogo multimillonario que desprecia todo lo que representa el proyecto europeo.</PARA><PARA>Señorías, estamos ante un momento transformador. Este es el momento de levantar la voz, de defender con orgullo el proyecto europeo y de demostrar que, frente al caos, la Unión Europea es la esperanza de un orden justo, democrático y sostenible.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="FR" INDEX="2-0013-0000" ACT="2017023813495" PRE="2017023813493" SUIV="2017023813497" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:29:16" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:31:57"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Jordan | Bardella" PP="PfE" LG="FR" MEPID="131580" CODICT="131580" SPEAKER_TYPE="au nom du groupe"><LG>FR</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Jordan Bardella, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">au nom du groupe PfE</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, rien n&apos;a été anticipé, et pourtant l&apos;Europe semble découvrir ce qui était annoncé depuis bien longtemps: conformément à son projet, Donald Trump utilise les droits de douane comme une arme pour faire plier aussi bien ses partenaires que ses concurrents.</PARA><PARA>En frappant sans distinction presque tous les secteurs et tous les États, le président américain crée des incertitudes et des fragilités supplémentaires pour nos entrepreneurs. L&apos;heure n&apos;est cependant pas à la déploration; l&apos;heure est à la riposte, à la réponse et à la défense de nos intérêts économiques.</PARA><PARA>À court terme, il est dans notre bon droit de riposter par des droits de douane gradués, qui seront un moyen de pression pour négocier et obtenir un retour à la normale. L&apos;Europe est un marché de 450 millions de consommateurs et il serait incompréhensible qu&apos;elle reste les bras ballants. La véritable riposte consiste en une rupture claire avec au moins trois décennies d&apos;errance, une rupture avec les choix de la Commission européenne.</PARA><PARA>Alors que nous sommes entrés dans l&apos;ère des affrontements, l&apos;Europe ne peut plus être la seule puissance à respecter des règles internationales de bienséance que plus personne n&apos;applique. Face à la concurrence féroce des puissances, et notamment des puissances émergentes, dans l&apos;adversité d&apos;un monde plus dur et plus incertain, je vous en conjure, réveillez-vous!</PARA><PARA>Réveillez-vous ou bien notre agriculture disparaîtra. Réveillez-vous, ou bien notre industrie automobile mettra la clé sous la porte, notre métallurgie subira une saignée plus terrible encore – je pense évidemment ici aux salariés d&apos;ArcelorMittal, condamnés par une inaction coupable et par des règles absurdes. Réveillez-vous en bâtissant l&apos;autonomie stratégique des nations et du continent, avec l&apos;objectif de dépendre le moins possible de l&apos;extérieur pour nos besoins vitaux, à commencer par celui de notre défense.</PARA><PARA>Toutes les règles contraignantes du pacte vert inspirées par l&apos;écologie punitive doivent être levées pour permettre à nos entreprises et à nos agriculteurs, notamment, de produire sans entraves. Les règles du marché européen de l&apos;électricité doivent être réformées et le nucléaire doit prendre toute sa place dans notre bouquet énergétique. Une véritable préférence nationale et européenne dans les commandes publiques doit s&apos;appliquer, notamment en matière de défense, mais pas uniquement.</PARA><PARA>Réveillez-vous! Réveillez-vous et sortez de la naïveté, ou bien l&apos;Europe et toutes les nations qui la composent sortiront de l&apos;histoire.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="IT" INDEX="2-0014-0000" ACT="2017023813497" PRE="2017023813495" SUIV="2017023813499" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:32:05" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:34:07"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Nicola | Procaccini" PP="ECR" LG="IT" MEPID="197820" CODICT="197820" SPEAKER_TYPE="au nom du groupe"><LG>IT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Nicola Procaccini, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">a nome del gruppo ECR</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, noi conservatori crediamo nel libero mercato che favorisce allo stesso tempo i consumatori e i produttori, quelli naturalmente più capaci, con più talento. Ma dobbiamo ammettere che la politica dei dazi è stata anche una politica europea, che non si è rivolta soltanto verso chi viola ogni giorno la libera concorrenza, come la Cina, ma anche nei confronti di alleati preziosi come i cittadini americani.</PARA><PARA>Faccio un solo esempio: fino a poche settimane fa gli Stati Uniti ponevano un dazio del 2,5 % sulle auto europee. L&apos;Unione europea poneva un dazio del 10 % sulle auto americane. Da qui bisogna partire per un accordo con gli Stati Uniti di libero scambio con zero dazi da ambo le parti. È ciò di cui ha discusso Meloni con Trump a Washington dentro un quadro politico generale in cui va preservata l&apos;unità dell&apos;Occidente. Il riequilibrio della bilancia commerciale con gli Stati Uniti non è solo un fatto economico, è anche politico.</PARA><PARA>Lo scandalo del gas liquido dalla Russia è emblematico di una certa ipocrisia europea e soltanto oggi il commissario Jørgensen sembra intenzionato ad occuparsene. Sapete quali sono le nazioni che hanno più arricchito Putin negli ultimi anni con l&apos;acquisto di GNL? Beh, non è l&apos;Ungheria di Orban ma è la Francia di Macron, con un incremento dell&apos;81 % tra il 2024 e il 2023.</PARA><PARA>Ed è la Spagna <EMPHAS NAME="I">green</EMPHAS> di Sánchez che con il 38 % ha nella Russia il suo maggiore fornitore di gas. Ecco un&apos;altra cosa giusta da fare: rimuovere i dazi che l&apos;Unione europea ha inflitto a se stessa con il <EMPHAS NAME="I">Green Deal</EMPHAS> e così rilanciare la sua competitività. Questa è la strada che dobbiamo percorrere; non certo quella che va verso regimi illiberali come la Cina o la Corea del Nord.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="FR" INDEX="2-0015-0000" ACT="2017023813499" PRE="2017023813497" SUIV="2017023813502" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:34:13" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:37:50"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Valérie | Hayer" PP="Renew" LG="FR" MEPID="135511" CODICT="135511" SPEAKER_TYPE="au nom du groupe"><LG>FR</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Valérie Hayer, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">au nom du groupe Renew</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Vice-Président, Monsieur le Ministre, chers collègues, «le vieux monde se meurt, le nouveau tarde à apparaître et dans ce clair-obscur surgissent les monstres»: cette citation d&apos;Antonio Gramsci est la parfaite métaphore du défi posé par la guerre commerciale de Donald Trump.</PARA><PARA>Cette guerre commerciale interroge l&apos;identité même de l&apos;Union européenne. Elle est, au-delà du péril immense qu&apos;elle représente pour nos économies, un défi politique, une confrontation entre deux modèles, le modèle promu par cette nouvelle administration américaine – protectionnisme, brutalité, populisme – et notre modèle européen – liberté, force du droit, démocratie. Le «Make America great again» est une attaque frontale contre le multilatéralisme. C&apos;est une attaque frontale contre une Europe dans laquelle 27 pays jouent le jeu de la coopération. C&apos;est une attaque frontale contre ce que nous avons construit ensemble au lendemain de la Seconde Guerre mondiale. Oui, chers collègues, le commerce mondial régulé est un outil de paix durable, le plus puissant que nous ayons jamais connu. Pourtant, Donald Trump a décidé de lancer une guerre commerciale à la terre entière; à la terre entière, hormis la Russie, la Biélorussie et la Corée du Nord.</PARA><PARA>Alors, je voudrais dire trois choses au président américain: premièrement, la guerre commerciale ne profite à personne et en aucun cas aux consommateurs américains qui sont les premiers à en payer le prix. Deuxièmement, l&apos;Europe sera toujours un partenaire commercial juste et fiable, dans le respect des règles internationales. Troisièmement, s&apos;il faut jouer le rapport de force, alors nous y sommes prêts.</PARA><PARA>Vous l&apos;avez rappelé, Monsieur le Vice-Président, nous avons tous les outils de défense commerciale pour protéger nos concitoyens et nos entreprises. C&apos;est notre position. Sans jamais fermer la porte à la négociation, la Commission européenne doit être prête à se saisir de ces instruments.</PARA><PARA>Chers collègues, la bataille culturelle imposée par Donald Trump oblige chacun à se positionner, y compris dans cet hémicycle. Certains d&apos;entre vous étaient à Washington le soir même de son élection. Beaucoup ont appelé à un trumpisme, à la française ou à l&apos;européenne. Certains, d&apos;ailleurs, sont bien embarrassés aujourd&apos;hui, comme c&apos;est le cas des orateurs qui m&apos;ont précédée. Ce sont les mêmes qui rêvent d&apos;un repli sur les frontières nationales et d&apos;un retour au protectionnisme économique. Je veux vous dire: ouvrez les yeux, cela ne marche pas! Voyez par vous-mêmes que cela ne peut pas marcher.</PARA><PARA>Ce que nous défendons ici, c&apos;est un commerce mondial régulé. Ce sont des accords de commerce conclus sur des bases de réciprocité qui ne mettent pas en péril nos agriculteurs ou nos industries, des accords de commerce qui permettent au contraire de diversifier nos approvisionnements en matières premières ou nos débouchés économiques. C&apos;est la garantie de notre prospérité pour les années qui viennent.</PARA><PARA>Dans cette période, chers collègues, l&apos;Europe est tout sauf faible. Nous avons un marché de 450 millions d&apos;Européens, attractif pour de nombreux pays qui veulent renforcer leurs relations avec nous. Nous avons un cadre législatif et réglementaire qui offre une visibilité rassurante pour de nombreux investisseurs.</PARA><PARA>Alors ne laissons pas les monstres surgir du clair-obscur. Ne laissons pas l&apos;Europe dévier de son chemin. Construisons les bases d&apos;un monde nouveau où l&apos;Union européenne répond au défi de sa souveraineté.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0016-0000" ACT="2017023813502" PRE="2017023813499" SUIV="2017023813504" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:37:59" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:40:31"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Bas | Eickhout" PP="Verts/ALE" LG="EN" MEPID="96725" CODICT="96725" SPEAKER_TYPE="au nom du groupe"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Bas Eickhout, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Mr President, Commissioner, Minister, let&apos;s be very clear. The illegal tariffs that are imposed and announced by the Trump administration will not only hurt Europeans, they will also hurt US consumers and businesses. Trump is playing a stupid but dangerous game.</PARA><PARA>If the current negotiations do not work – and the Commissioner already said it – the EU has to show its strength and retaliate firmly. We have the instruments to do so. It comes down to political will and leadership. We should not back down to a bully.</PARA><PARA>Important in our reaction is solidarity amongst EU Member States, because it&apos;s key. We will have to stay united, and therefore the money raised by countermeasures should be invested to support the affected sectors in all countries, in order to keep the unity.</PARA><PARA>However, we have to be smarter than just bashing Trump on his favourite words. We need to develop a strategy that will make Europe stronger and more resilient in the new, chaotic world we are living in; a strategy that should build on the Green Deal that we have put in as a forward-looking and future-oriented strategy.</PARA><PARA>But, on top of that, we need to have three principles in mind. First, we need to build European. We are overly dependent on US energy, defence, financial and digital services. Only strong and common European alternatives can provide us the operating room we need. We need joint investments in those sectors. We need joint EU borrowing measures.</PARA><PARA>Secondly, we need to buy European. In the past months, the European consumers showed the way in showing how you do not buy further Teslas. We should learn from them and use local content requirements and resilience criteria, and give preference to European products and services.</PARA><PARA>Thirdly, we need to protect European – our values, our industry. They will only survive if we act and protect, if we apply our digital rights to the letter, if we stop dumping on the EU market.</PARA><PARA>We will work together with those that still value our rules-based system. Let that be our strategy. Build European, buy European, protect European. Europe needs to stop thinking as a market and start acting as a power – a power to do good.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="DE" INDEX="2-0017-0000" ACT="2017023813504" PRE="2017023813502" SUIV="2017023813506" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:40:38" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:44:10"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Martin | Schirdewan" PP="The Left" LG="DE" MEPID="190517" CODICT="190517" SPEAKER_TYPE="au nom du groupe"><LG>DE</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Martin Schirdewan, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">im Namen der Fraktion The Left</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Herr Präsident! Donald Trump hat es geschafft, in den ersten hundert Tagen seiner Präsidentschaft die internationalen Handelsbeziehungen komplett zu chaotisieren. Die Folgen für Wirtschaft und die Bevölkerung sind bereits absehbar. Die Wirtschaftsleistung wird zurückgehen, und gleichzeitig werden sich die Preise verteuern. Die Zeche dafür werden zuallererst wieder die arbeitende Bevölkerung zahlen und diejenigen, die sowieso wenig Geld in der Tasche haben.</PARA><PARA>Diese Politik ist kein Zufall. Der Rechtspopulist Donald Trump versucht gezielt, die Interessen seiner Wirtschaftskumpels, nämlich der US‑Rüstungsindustrie, der US‑Energieriesen und der US‑Big‑Tech‑Unternehmen durchzusetzen. Aber die Europäische Kommission scheint das noch gar nicht wirklich begriffen zu haben. Herr Kommissar, wir befinden uns in einem globalen Handelskrieg, und dabei wird Handelspolitik als eine Waffe eingesetzt, um wirtschaftliche Interessen durchzusetzen und international Einflusssphären abzustecken. Dem muss europäische Politik mit einer klaren Strategie begegnen, die Wirtschaft und Jobs hier in der Europäischen Union schützt, und das geht nur mit massiven Investitionen in unsere Industrie. Das geht nur mit strategischer Unabhängigkeit der Europäischen Union.</PARA><PARA>Heute wissen auch Sie, Herr Kommissar, dass die anfängliche Kopf‑in‑den‑Sand‑Strategie der Kommission à la „Es wird schon nicht so schlimm werden” politische Realitätsverweigerung war. Jetzt wollen Sie verhandeln, einen Deal auch im Sinne von Donald Trump abschließen, und wenn das nicht klappen sollte, dann soll es angeblich harte Gegenmaßnahmen geben.</PARA><PARA>Von Angeboten Ihrerseits höre ich viel, die gibt es reichlich. Jetzt soll sogar noch mehr US‑Fracking-Gas gekauft werden – anstatt die europäische Energieunabhängigkeit voranzutreiben und so viele Jobs zu schaffen, wird eine neue Abhängigkeit von fossilen Energieträgern geschaffen. Das ist ökonomisch, sozial und ökologisch grundfalsch. Aber von dem Druck auf die US‑Regierung ist noch nichts zu sehen. Wo bleibt denn die Einführung des Instruments gegen Zwangsmaßnahmen? Wo bleibt denn die harte Regulierung der großen Big‑Tech‑Unternehmen? Wo bleibt die Einführung einer europäischen Digitalsteuer? Da machen Sie die Augen zu, da legen Sie die Hände hinter dem Rücken zusammen. Wollen Sie denn auf diese Art und Weise den reichsten Unternehmen und Menschen wie Elon Musk noch mehr Geld und vor allem auch unsere privaten Daten in den Rachen werfen?</PARA><PARA>Es ist jetzt an der Zeit, mit Partnern wie Kanada, Mexiko, Japan, Südkorea, aber auch mit China an einer Handelsordnung zu wirken, die regelbasiert ist, auf fairem Handel statt auf entfesseltem Freihandel basiert. Und alles, was der EU‑Kommission da einzufallen scheint, sind Rohstoffabkommen wie das mit Ruanda, das maßgeblich zu einer Verschärfung des Krieges im Kongo beiträgt, oder digitale Kooperationsabkommen wie das mit Singapur, das unsere Datensicherheit unterläuft, oder aber klassische Freihandelsabkommen wie mit Mercosur, denen die Europäer schon seit TTIP die Rote Karte gezeigt haben, weil sie schlecht für soziale Standards, Umwelt und Landwirtschaft sind. Ihre Antwort auf Trump dient einzig und allein den US‑Oligarchen und den europäischen Oligarchen. Wir brauchen eine Antwort, die der Mehrheit der Bevölkerung und der Demokratie dient.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="DE" INDEX="2-0018-0000" ACT="2017023813506" PRE="2017023813504" SUIV="2017023813507" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:44:17" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:46:54"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="René | Aust" PP="ESN" LG="DE" MEPID="256929" CODICT="256929" SPEAKER_TYPE="au nom du groupe"><LG>DE</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">René Aust, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">im Namen der ESN-Fraktion</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Herr Präsident, meine sehr geehrten Damen und Herren! Wer nach außen abhängig ist, wird nach außen handlungsunfähig. Und genau das ist eingetreten – nicht zufällig, sondern weil die Altparteien unsere militärische Sicherheit über Jahrzehnte den Vereinigten Staaten von Amerika überlassen haben. Das war bequem, aber es war auch naiv. Heute sehen wir das Ergebnis: Europa ist erpressbar geworden. Die Regierung unter Donald Trump versucht, Europa zum Kauf von immer mehr US‑Fracking‑Gas zu nötigen. Die Folge: noch höhere Energiepreise zulasten unserer Industrie, unserer Familien und unseres Wohlstandes.</PARA><PARA>Und es rächt sich auch das überhebliche Gehabe, mit dem viele in der europäischen Politik über Jahre hinweg auf Donald Trump herabgesehen haben. Die öffentlichen Angriffe haben dazu geführt, dass heute weder in Brüssel noch in Berlin oder Paris vertrauensvolle Gesprächskanäle zur US‑Regierung bestehen. Ein Glück, dass es in Europa auch andere Stimmen gibt – Viktor Orbán, Georgia Meloni und viele patriotische Regierungen –, die den Kontakt gepflegt haben.</PARA><PARA>Doch es geht nicht nur um Amerika. Auch Handelsalternativen wurden fahrlässig zerstört durch Besserwisserei gegenüber China, gegenüber Indien und weiten Teilen Afrikas. Statt Partnerschaft gab es Belehrungen über Demokratie, über Menschenrechte, über Klima. Und heute? Heute fehlen uns genau diese Partner als Alternativen, die wir bräuchten, um in Verhandlungen mit den USA Stärke zeigen zu können. Denn wer keine Alternativen hat, hat auch keine Verhandlungsmacht. Das europäische Establishment hat unseren Kontinent durch Arroganz isoliert. Doch wer im 21. Jahrhundert bestehen will, braucht Kooperation statt Konfrontation, Partnerschaften, nicht Feindbilder.</PARA><PARA>Und noch etwas: Heute zeigt sich, wie wichtig der europäische Binnenmarkt ist. Zu diesem haben wir uns als AfD immer bekannt. Unser Motto lautet: Deutschland zuerst, aber nicht Deutschland allein. Europa muss in zentralen Handelsfragen mit einer Stimme sprechen. Aber das setzt auch eines voraus, nämlich: Das europäische Establishment muss die Spaltung nach innen beenden. Erkennen Sie das Wahlergebnis in Rumänien an! Hören Sie auf, sich aus Brüssel heraus in die inneren Angelegenheiten Ungarns einzumischen, und stoppen Sie die Verfolgung der AfD in Deutschland!</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="SK" INDEX="2-0019-0000" ACT="2017023813507" PRE="2017023813506" SUIV="2017023813508" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:46:53" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:47:23"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Predsedajúci " PP="NULL" LG="SK" MEPID="197770" CODICT="197770"><LG>SK</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Predsedajúci .</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – A nakoľko nám skončilo prvé kolo vystupujúcich za politické skupiny a otvárame blue card.</PARA><PARA>I would also like to inform you that I will have to be more strict as regards the usual courtesy of giving a bit more speaking time, with more tolerance towards the speakers of the political groups. But now, due to the time, we will have to be a bit more strict.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0021-0000" ACT="2017023813508" PRE="2017023813507" SUIV="2017023813510" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:47:22" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:49:06"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Michał | Szczerba" PP="PPE" LG="EN" MEPID="257026" CODICT="257026"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Michał Szczerba (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, Commissioner, Minister, colleagues, nowadays the world is getting increasingly less predictable. In my country, Poland, people are asking what happens next? Should we be afraid of Russian aggression? Are Europe&apos;s relations with the US on a crisis course? Will Europe be able to quickly boost its defence capabilities? The future of transatlantic relations depends on our current actions. This is exactly why we, as Europeans, are taking more responsibility for our security. To build defence potential requires a strong economy. The imposition of tariffs by the US on EU exports do not help. We see no justification for this. Mutual imposition of tariffs on our economies is not our shared interest.</PARA><PARA>My statement as a standing rapporteur for the US is crystal clear: transatlantic cooperation is beneficial for both sides of the Atlantic. Whether we talk about security or economy, no other economies in the world are integrated in such an advanced way. The EU and the US are the largest trade and investment partners. Together, we represent 30 % of global trade in goods and services. Therefore, the trade wars will not benefit either side. That is why we cannot stop engaging in building strong dialogue. But let me be clear here: the imposition of tariffs will not only hurt Europeans, American businesses will be affected too.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0022-0000" ACT="2017023813510" PRE="2017023813508" SUIV="2017023813513" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:49:11" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:50:22"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Kathleen | Van Brempt" PP="S-D" LG="EN" MEPID="5729" CODICT="5729"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Kathleen Van Brempt (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, dear Commissioner, colleagues, the US, once the greatest defender of liberal democracy, is rapidly becoming an authoritarian regime. This is a huge challenge, but also an opportunity for the European Union. It is time to show our strength.</PARA><PARA>That is why we should support the WTO and intensify our contacts and trade with like-minded countries like the UK and Canada, and look for new sustainable partnerships in Asia and Latin America.</PARA><PARA>And, of course, we need to negotiate, but not at all costs. Dear Commissioner, can you guarantee that our legislation is not up for discussion with the US? And why are the tariffs on US services still not yet on the table? I think we need answers to that.</PARA><PARA>Above all, dear colleagues, the &apos;Trump show&apos; should not distract us from doing what is needed for Europe. That means providing support for workers, implementing the Green Deal and investing in our strategic economy. Because the world, dear colleagues, needs urgently a united and independent Europe to lead the way.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="ES" INDEX="2-0023-0000" ACT="2017023813513" PRE="2017023813510" SUIV="2017023813515" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:50:26" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:52:09"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Jorge | Buxadé Villalba" PP="PfE" LG="ES" MEPID="197829" CODICT="197829"><LG>ES</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Jorge Buxadé Villalba (<PP>PfE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Señor presidente, esto no va de aranceles ni de barreras comerciales. Esto va de a quién le colocan el muerto de la economía europea.</PARA><PARA>No es cierto que vivamos en un régimen internacional de libre comercio que está en peligro. Los aranceles, las cuotas a la importación y las barreras regulatorias son la regla general. China subió los aranceles al porcino hace unos meses y ustedes no dijeron ni pío. Es Bruselas la que lleva décadas levantando barreras y cargas contra nuestros productores en nombre de la Pachamama.</PARA><PARA>Competimos con las manos atadas mientras China, Turquía y Marruecos golpean con los dos puños. Y ustedes, socialistas y populares, son los responsables. Le niegan agua a Almería o Murcia, pero financian obras hídricas en Marruecos. Ustedes expropian cientos de miles de olivos en España para poner placas solares, ustedes prohíben a la industria vender coches con motores de combustión en 2035. Ustedes montaron un negocio especulativo de derechos de emisión de CO<EMPHAS NAME="SUB">2</EMPHAS> que ahoga a nuestras industrias por razones climáticas y un mecanismo de ajuste en frontera que es una barrera no arancelaria. Ustedes se meten en los consejos de administración debajo de las mesas a mirar el sexo de los administradores. Ustedes solo piensan en subir impuestos para pagar la juerga de las élites y se han gastado nuestro dinero en renovables chinas. Y en España ya no tenemos luz.</PARA><PARA>Para ustedes, el libre comercio es rendirse con China. Para ustedes, libre comercio son esos acuerdos con países que no cumplen los estándares que se exigen a los nuestros. Por supuesto que rechazamos cualquier arancel a nuestros productores, pero primero y por encima de todo, rechazamos su Agenda 2030, su Pacto Verde y su hipocresía de fanáticos climáticos.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0024-0000" ACT="2017023813515" PRE="2017023813513" SUIV="2017023813517" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:52:14" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:53:22"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Adam | Bielan" PP="ECR" LG="EN" MEPID="23788" CODICT="23788"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Adam Bielan (<PP>ECR</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, dear Commissioner, let me start by thanking Prime Minister Giorgia Meloni for making the strategic decision to visit Washington at a critical moment for our transatlantic relations. While others choose ambiguity, she acted – because leadership means showing up.</PARA><PARA>Unfortunately, the same cannot be said for the Polish Prime Minister, Donald Tusk, who continues to block President Duda&apos;s initiative to hold a long overdue EU-US summit in Warsaw under the Polish Presidency in the Council.</PARA><PARA>This is a missed opportunity, both symbolically and politically. Cancelling the summit sends the wrong signal to our most important ally, especially as global tensions rise and our need for unity grows. Yes, we may have disagreements with the US on trade subsidies and regulatory divergence, but the answer should not be retaliation. The answer should be pragmatic engagement. We need a common strategic European response that both protects our interests and strengthens our partnership.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="SV" INDEX="2-0025-0000" ACT="2017023813517" PRE="2017023813515" SUIV="2017023813519" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:53:30" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:55:16"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Karin | Karlsbro" PP="Renew" LG="SV" MEPID="197401" CODICT="197401"><LG>SV</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Karin Karlsbro (<PP>Renew</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Herr talman! Hur botar man Trumpångest? Det bästa receptet är ett starkt EU. Ett Europa som står upp för allt det där som gör den här planeten lite bättre: demokrati, frihandel, vetenskap, upplysning, rättsstat, jämställdhet. Eller enkelt uttryckt: det som kallas liberalism.</PARA><PARA>Sedan president Trump flyttade in i Vita huset har vi sett en amerikansk president som ägnat all sin kraft åt att sabotera relationerna med sina bästa vänner, som med en aggressiv kampanjdiplomati hotar både den globala världsordningen och enskilda länder, som startar handelskrig och som bedriver ett ekonomiskt experiment med våra plånböcker och våra pensioner genom att införa höga tullar. Vi är redo att slå tillbaka.</PARA><PARA>När Trump sviker och Putin hotar Europa behöver vi hålla ihop. Ett starkare EU som försvarar Europas, Sveriges och Ukrainas intressen är det vi behöver. När USA till och med höjer tullarna mot Ukraina ska vi jobba för att få bort dem. När USA försöker härska genom att splittra EU ska vi stärka den inre marknaden och handla mer med varandra. I dag har EU flest handelsavtal i världen med totalt 74 länder. Fler är på gång. Hur många nya avtal har Donald Trump? Noll.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="DE" INDEX="2-0026-0000" ACT="2017023813519" PRE="2017023813517" SUIV="2017023813521" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:55:22" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:57:10"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Anna | Cavazzini" PP="Verts/ALE" LG="DE" MEPID="86793" CODICT="86793"><LG>DE</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Anna Cavazzini (<PP>Verts/ALE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Herr Präsident, lieber Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Es macht mir große Sorgen, dass Trumps Zollkrieg Jobs vernichtet, der Wirtschaft schadet, die Preise steigen lässt, und das vor allem in den USA. Und es macht mir extrem große Sorgen, dass in den USA gerade ein rechtsnationaler <EMPHAS NAME="I">powergrab</EMPHAS> stattfindet, der Stück für Stück Demokratie und Rechtsstaatlichkeit abschafft.</PARA><PARA>Und es ist so wichtig, dass die EU in diesem Chaos geschlossen agiert. Als größter Markt der Welt haben wir eine riesige Macht, und die sollten wir nicht kleinreden. Lassen wir uns von der aktuellen Zollpause nicht blenden. Viele von Trumps Zöllen, die sind bereits in Kraft, und deswegen müssen wir jetzt gezielte Gegenmaßnahmen auf den Weg bringen, wenn er die aktuellen Zölle nicht zurücknimmt. Dazu gehört auch eine Besteuerung der großen Digitalkonzerne.</PARA><PARA>Klar muss die Kommission gleichzeitig weiter versuchen, zu verhandeln. Aber auf keinen Fall dürfen wir unsere Standards senken und unsere europäischen Gesetze aufweichen. Das gilt für die Regulierung von Techgiganten genauso wie für die Landwirtschaftsimporte und für die Regeln zu Methan. Neue LNG-Importe – ich weiß nicht, ob das eine gute Idee ist. Der zu erwartenden massiven Umlenkung aus China müssen wir mit robusten Schutzmaßnahmen begegnen.</PARA><PARA>Ja, wir müssen die Handelspartner diversifizieren. Aber für mich heißt das vor allen Dingen, den Binnenmarkt zu stärken, die Nachfrage hier zu stärken. Ich sage ganz klar: Trumps Zollpolitik kann nicht die Ausrede dafür sein, dass wir bei neuen Handelsabkommen unsere Standards über Bord werfen und der weiteren Auslagerung von Industrieproduktion Tür und Tor öffnen. Bei aller Kritik an Trump dürfen wir nicht vergessen, dass sich in den USA in beiden Lagern eine riesige Unzufriedenheit über die Globalisierung Bahn bricht. Und das darf in Europa nicht passieren.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="FR" INDEX="2-0027-0000" ACT="2017023813521" PRE="2017023813519" SUIV="2017023813523" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:57:16" VOD-END="2025-05-06T09:58:33"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Manon | Aubry" PP="The Left" LG="FR" MEPID="197533" CODICT="197533"><LG>FR</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Manon Aubry (<PP>The Left</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, avec la guerre commerciale initiée par Donald Trump, nous sommes en train de vivre un bouleversement économique historique. Face à cela, que proposez-vous? Premièrement, de ne jamais hausser le ton face à un président américain qui multiplie les violations du droit international. Deuxièmement, de céder au chantage – à son chantage – en achetant 50 milliards de produits américains supplémentaires, histoire qu&apos;il nous vende la pelle avec laquelle nous creusons notre propre tombe. Troisièmement, d&apos;accélérer la signature de nouveaux accords commerciaux, pour commencer avec les États-Unis, mais aussi avec le Mercosur, l&apos;Inde, la Thaïlande, l&apos;Australie, et j&apos;en passe.</PARA><PARA>Bref, on vient de se prendre une baffe et vous tendez l&apos;autre joue. Traduction: le libre-échange est mort, vive le libre-échange! Allons-y, rendons-nous encore plus dépendants du reste du monde, comme si nous n&apos;avions rien appris de cette crise. Surtout, sacrifions encore un peu plus toujours les mêmes: les travailleurs, les travailleurs des industries que vous jetez en pâture, Monsieur le Commissaire. Plus que jamais, l&apos;impasse du libre-échange et de la mondialisation capitaliste saute aux yeux. Sortons de ce système mortifère.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="DE" INDEX="2-0028-0000" ACT="2017023813523" PRE="2017023813521" SUIV="2017023813525" VOD-START="2025-05-06T09:58:39" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:01:12"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Petr | Bystron" PP="ESN" LG="DE" MEPID="256928" CODICT="256928"><LG>DE</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Petr Bystron (<PP>ESN</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Herr Präsident, liebe Kolleginnen, liebe Kollegen! „<EMPHAS NAME="I">Make America great again</EMPHAS>″ ist natürlich eine Kampfansage an die ganze Welt, an die EU, an Europa. Warum? Der amerikanische Präsident kümmert sich natürlich um die Amerikaner – oh Wunder! Er will Arbeitsplätze in den Vereinigten Staaten. Er will, dass Wohlstand wieder in den Vereinigten Staaten zurück ist. Er will die Industrie in die Vereinigten Staaten zurückholen. Und was höre ich hier? Trump, Trump, Trump! Ein einziger Mann reicht, um das Europäische Parlament in Aufruhr zu versetzen.</PARA><PARA>Liebe Kollegen, anstatt zu jammern und über Trump herzuziehen, sollten Sie von den Altparteien lieber überlegen: Was haben Sie gemacht? Wann haben Sie das letzte Mal für Ihre Wähler so gekämpft wie Trump für seine amerikanischen? Die Frage ist berechtigt, denn Trumps Reaktion ist nur eine logische Entwicklung der letzten Jahrzehnte. Die Arbeitsplätze, nicht nur aus den USA, auch aus Europa, sind abgewandert in Billiglohnländer. Das haben unsere Menschen, unsere Arbeiter zu spüren bekommen, genauso wie die Amerikaner. Zuerst in der Stahlindustrie, dann in der Elektronikindustrie, in der Automobilindustrie, und jetzt zuletzt sind sogar unsere Bauern dran.</PARA><PARA>Wie ist unsere Reaktion? Wollen wir in einen Handelskrieg eintreten? Wollen wir mit künstlicher Verteuerung der Importe reagieren? Natürlich nicht! Wir brauchen den freien Handel, wir wollen den freien Handel. Und Europa – und damit meine ich nicht die EU –, Europa kann diesen Wettbewerb aufnehmen. Wir haben die besser ausgebildeten Arbeitskräfte, wir haben eine innovative Industrie, wir haben Rohstoffe auf diesem Kontinent, wir können diesen Wettbewerb aufnehmen, aber wir müssen die Fesseln sprengen, die uns hier bremsen. Wir müssen den <EMPHAS NAME="I">Green Deal</EMPHAS> beenden, Steuern runter, und wir müssen das Bürokratiemonster Brüssel zerschlagen. „Afuera“, das ist das Motto der Zeit, und dann kann unser Motto heißen: „<EMPHAS NAME="I">Make Europe great again</EMPHAS>“.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="DE" INDEX="2-0029-0000" ACT="2017023813525" PRE="2017023813523" SUIV="2017023813532" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:01:17" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:02:52"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Fabio | De Masi" PP="NI" LG="DE" MEPID="124858" CODICT="124858"><LG>DE</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Fabio De Masi (<PP>NI</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Herr Präsident, sehr geehrte Damen und Herren! US-Präsident Donald Trump versucht, uns mit Strafzöllen zu erpressen. Er will, dass wir mehr von seinem schmutzigen Fracking-Gas kaufen. Und er will den Abstieg der US-Industrie bremsen. Aber wir in Europa, wir sind nur bedingt ökonomisch verteidigungsfähig, denn wir haben zum Beispiel in Deutschland, der größten Volkswirtschaft Europas, seit drei Jahren Rezession. Wir haben uns mit den Sanktionen mehr selbst geschadet, als dass wir damit Putin getroffen hätten. Wir haben Verbrauchssteuern erhöht, die vor allem die Menschen mit kleinem Einkommen treffen. Und währenddessen besorgen sich die USA jetzt die Seltenen Erden aus der Ukraine, während wir als Zahlmeister am Spielfeldrand stehen.</PARA><PARA>Auch die Transformation zum grünen Stahl, die kann nicht gelingen, wenn die Energiepreise weiter so hoch sind. Deswegen müssen wir zu dem Prinzip zurückkehren, zu sagen: Wir besorgen uns die Energie wieder vom billigsten Anbieter. Das wäre die richtige Antwort auf Donald Trump, um uns nicht weiter erpressbar zu machen. Und es würde ein diplomatisches Fenster in der Ukraine öffnen. Wir brauchen mehr öffentliche Investitionen. Es ist doch völlig verrückt, wenn in den Talkshows nun darüber diskutiert wird, wir sollten Panzer statt Volkswagen bauen. Und wir brauchen Strafsteuern auf Finanzflüsse der Big-Tech-Unternehmen, um unseren Mittelstand zu schützen.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO INDEX="2-0030-0000" ACT="2017023813532" PRE="2017023813525" SUIV="2017023813528" VL="ES"/><PRES><EMPHAS NAME="B">PRESIDE: ESTEBAN GONZÁLEZ PONS</EMPHAS><BRK/><EMPHAS NAME="I">Vicepresidente</EMPHAS></PRES><NUMERO VL="DE" INDEX="2-0031-0000" ACT="2017023813528" PRE="2017023813532" SUIV="2017023813529" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:02:50" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:03:23"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Lukas | Sieper" PP="NI" LG="DE" MEPID="256971" CODICT="256971"><LG>DE</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Lukas Sieper (<PP>NI</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Vielen Dank, Herr Kollege, dass Sie die blaue Karte akzeptiert haben. Sie haben gesagt: Wir sollen uns die Energie wieder vom billigsten Anbieter besorgen. Ich nehme mal an, Sie meinen damit die Russen. Trotz des russischen Angriffskriegs, trotz der russischen Kriegsverbrechen, trotz der Deportation von Hunderttausenden Kindern. Ohne jetzt auf diese konkrete Frage einzugehen, würde ich deswegen mal gerne so Ihr generelles moralisches Verständnis abstecken. Was darf denn ein Energieanbieter tun, damit wir uns die Energie nicht mehr von ihm besorgen, nur weil es dann billiger ist?</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="DE" INDEX="2-0032-0000" ACT="2017023813529" PRE="2017023813528" SUIV="2017023813530" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:03:23" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:04:12"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Fabio | De Masi" PP="NI" LG="DE" MEPID="124858" CODICT="124858"><LG>DE</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Fabio De Masi (<PP>NI</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Nun, die Frage der Moral, die richtet sich danach, welches Instrument geeignet ist, den Ukrainekrieg so schnell wie möglich zu beenden. Und wenn wir uns ökonomisch mehr schaden, als dass wir die Fähigkeit Putins, einen Krieg zu führen, beeinträchtigen, dann ist das einfach keine sinnvolle Politik. Wir haben selbstverständlich nach dem Irakkrieg nicht angefangen, die USA zu sanktionieren, weil wir uns damit selbst ins Knie geschossen hätten.</PARA><PARA>Deswegen ist das keine moralische Frage, sondern eine Frage der politischen Logik, dass wir eine Politik machen, die den Menschen in Europa dient. Und wenn sie eben nicht zum gewünschten Ergebnis führt, dann kann ja eine Entspannung der Sanktionen auch ein Instrument sein, um zu einem Waffenstillstand zu gelangen. Deswegen sind jene unmoralisch, die diesen Krieg unnötig verlängern wollen und immer mehr Blut und Leichenberge in Kauf nehmen.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0033-0000" ACT="2017023813530" PRE="2017023813529" SUIV="2017023813531" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:04:12" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:04:37"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="President" PP="NULL" LG="EN" MEPID="125027" CODICT="125027"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">President.</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Excuse me, because I should have not given the floor to Mr Sieper, because he belongs to the same group as Mr De Masi, which is the non-attached Members. So sorry for giving him the blue card.</PARA><PARA>No, thank you. It&apos;s very clear in the Rules.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="ES" INDEX="2-0034-0000" ACT="2017023813531" PRE="2017023813530" SUIV="2017023813534" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:04:36" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:05:52"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Juan Ignacio | Zoido Álvarez" PP="PPE" LG="ES" MEPID="197621" CODICT="197621"><LG>ES</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Juan Ignacio Zoido Álvarez (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Señor presidente, señorías, que los aranceles nos conducen al desastre no es ninguna sorpresa. Lo dice la teoría económica más básica, lo dice la historia del comercio internacional y ahora lo vuelven a confirmar los datos. El precio de los productos afectados ha aumentado cerca de un 12 % para los consumidores. De continuar este encarecimiento, provocará una pérdida de 7 300 millones de dólares anuales, algo que ya está notándose en el empleo con la destrucción de 40 000 puestos de trabajo al otro lado del Atlántico.</PARA><PARA>Por tanto, el fracaso de los aranceles es ya manifiesto. De ahí que la suspensión haya sido por fin una medida racional por parte del señor Trump, necesaria tanto para estadounidenses como para europeos. Pero no podemos conformarnos con ella: necesitamos su eliminación definitiva, incluida la tasa del 10 %, que todavía sigue en vigor. No podemos permitir que la amenaza arancelaria penda sobre nuestras cabezas como una espada de Damocles. No podemos seguir poniendo en riesgo la seguridad jurídica de cientos de miles de productores europeos.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="DE" INDEX="2-0035-0000" ACT="2017023813534" PRE="2017023813531" SUIV="2017023813536" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:05:55" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:07:15"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Bernd | Lange" PP="S-D" LG="DE" MEPID="1909" CODICT="1909"><LG>DE</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Bernd Lange (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Herr Präsident, Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Es geht um drei „<EMPHAS NAME="I">ver-“</EMPHAS>. Wir müssen verteidigen, verbreiten und verhandeln. Verteidigen gegen illegale Zölle – und ich finde es gut, dass Sie alle Instrumente nutzen wollen, Herr Kommissar. Wir müssen verbreitern: unsere Basis mit vernünftigen Handelsabkommen, fairen Partnerschaften mit vielen Ländern dieser Erde. Auch da finde ich gut, dass Sie Neuigkeiten gebracht haben, auch was die Möglichkeiten eines Abkommens mit Indonesien anbetrifft. Und wir müssen schnell ratifizieren, um hier ein Netzwerk zu haben. Und wir müssen verhandeln – keine Frage –, weil wir natürlich die Eskalation vermeiden wollen. Aber es heißt auch, dass wir klarmachen: Diese Zölle sind illegal und müssen weg, auch bei den Autos. Es geht nicht nur um 2,5 Prozent und 10 Prozent, es geht auch um 25 Prozent Zölle auf leichte Nutzfahrzeuge in den USA, und deswegen müssen wir verhandeln. Die müssen weg, diese illegalen Zölle.</PARA><PARA>Deswegen wollen wir aber auch keine Möglichkeiten geben, unsere Gesetzgebung in Frage zu stellen. Und wir sind mit Ihnen einig, gemeinsam zu gehen. Allerdings müssen wir das Mandat für mögliche Verhandlungen und ein Ergebnis auch als Parlament billigen können.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="PL" INDEX="2-0036-0000" ACT="2017023813536" PRE="2017023813534" SUIV="2017023813538" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:07:20" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:08:58"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Anna | Bryłka" PP="NI" LG="PL" MEPID="257064" CODICT="257064"><LG>PL</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Anna Bryłka (<PP>NI</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Panie Przewodniczący! Panie Komisarzu! Stajemy dziś w obliczu kolejnej próby dla Unii Europejskiej, czyli odpowiedzi na jednostronne decyzje w polityce handlowej Stanów Zjednoczonych, które uderzają w interesy europejskich przedsiębiorstw. Współpraca transatlantycka jest dla nas ważna, ale musi być oparta na partnerstwie, a nie uległości. Przez lata Europa straciła swoją konkurencyjność. Gospodarka Unii rozwija się znacznie wolniej niż gospodarka amerykańska czy azjatycka. Unijne regulacje dławią innowacje. Polityka klimatyczna zwiększa koszty produkcji, a biurokracja zniechęca inwestorów.</PARA><PARA>W takich warunkach nie możemy mówić o suwerenności gospodarczej. Odpowiedzią nie może być więcej regulacji ani kolejne zielone transformacje, które przynoszą wyższe rachunki, a nie realne miejsca pracy. Musimy odbudować europejski przemysł, chronić nasz rynek i żądać równych zasad gry w relacjach z każdym partnerem, również ze Stanami Zjednoczonymi. Nie chodzi o konfrontację, ale o podmiotowość.</PARA><PARA>Europa musi przestać być laboratorium ideologii, a zacząć być realną siłą gospodarczą. Żeby to zrobić, trzeba zerwać z polityką prowadzoną od lat przez lewicowo-liberalną większość. Polityka handlowa Unii nie może być prowadzona na niemieckie zamówienie. Dlatego umowa o wolnym handlu Unia Europejska – Mercosur nadaje się tylko do kosza, bo likwiduje bezpieczeństwo żywnościowe Europy. Trzeba zapobiec wojnie handlowej. Musimy naprawić relacje ze Stanami Zjednoczonymi, bo to nadal największy sojusznik Europy i partner w ramach NATO.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="IT" INDEX="2-0037-0000" ACT="2017023813538" PRE="2017023813536" SUIV="2017023813540" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:09:04" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:10:23"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Daniele | Polato" PP="ECR" LG="IT" MEPID="257145" CODICT="257145"><LG>IT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Daniele Polato (<PP>ECR</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, le guerre commerciali non servono: infatti l&apos;amministrazione americana ha sospeso i dazi e questo è un messaggio positivo.</PARA><PARA>È essenziale riprendere i negoziati con gli Stati Uniti, come proposto a Washington dal Premier italiano, Giorgia Meloni: torniamo a dialogare ed offriamo spazi per un confronto equo e costruttivo. Per negoziare non dobbiamo lamentarci degli altri ma guardare al nostro operato interno rilanciando l&apos;economia europea.</PARA><PARA>Per anni abbiamo abbandonato e penalizzato settori strategici: industria, <EMPHAS NAME="I">automotive</EMPHAS>, agricoltura, chimica ed acciaio. Abbiamo perduto dinamicità e siamo diventati meno competitivi sui mercati mondiali, con limiti che ci siamo autoimposti. Senza un&apos;economia competitiva in ripresa, non avremo forza sui tavoli negoziali.</PARA><PARA>Occorre sviluppare accordi con nuovi mercati, proteggendoci da pratiche sleali di paesi terzi. Serve concretezza, pragmatismo, ascolto dei nostri imprenditori. Torniamo a rialzare la testa senza ideologie e pregiudizi. L&apos;Unione europea si muova in questa direzione.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="DE" INDEX="2-0038-0000" ACT="2017023813540" PRE="2017023813538" SUIV="2017023813542" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:10:27" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:11:34"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Svenja | Hahn" PP="Renew" LG="DE" MEPID="197444" CODICT="197444"><LG>DE</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Svenja Hahn (<PP>Renew</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Herr Präsident! Unser Ziel muss doch ganz klar der Freihandel bleiben. Aber die EU muss auch bereit sein, mit voller Härte im Handelskrieg zurückzuschlagen. Denn nur aus einer Position der Stärke heraus wird es mit jemandem wie Donald Trump eine Lösung geben. Wir müssen offen sein für pragmatische Lösungen, wir müssen aber vor allen Dingen endlich die Chancen ergreifen, die ganz offen vor uns liegen. Handelspolitik muss endlich pragmatischer werden, anstatt als ein Ersatz für eine fehlende EU‑Außenpolitik herzuhalten.</PARA><PARA>Wir müssen das Handelsabkommen mit Indien noch in diesem Jahr abschließen, das Abkommen mit Mexiko ratifizieren, und vor allen Dingen: Jedes EU‑Land, dass das CETA‑Abkommen mit Kanada noch nicht ratifiziert hat, muss es endlich tun. Ich habe vor allen Dingen kein Verständnis mehr für diese mythenreiche, aber faktenfreie Blockade vom Mercosur-Abkommen. Während Trump jedem Partner in der Welt vors Schienbein tritt, muss die EU doch ein Signal senden an alte und neue Partner in der Welt: Wir wollen mehr Handel mit euch! Das macht uns und unsere Partner wirtschaftlich und geopolitisch stärker.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="FR" INDEX="2-0039-0000" ACT="2017023813542" PRE="2017023813540" SUIV="2017023910544" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:11:39" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:12:59"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Saskia | Bricmont" PP="Verts/ALE" LG="FR" MEPID="197470" CODICT="197470"><LG>FR</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Saskia Bricmont (<PP>Verts/ALE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Monsieur le Président, l&apos;arrivée de Trump vient nous rappeler une leçon que l&apos;Europe aurait déjà dû tirer de la pandémie: notre ultradépendance aux énergies fossiles et aux marchés d&apos;approvisionnement mondiaux finira par causer notre perte. L&apos;Europe doit assurer son autonomie stratégique, répondre de manière ferme et unie à toute hausse des tarifs sans transiger sur ses législations et en utilisant les recettes de la hausse des tarifs, ainsi que celles d&apos;une taxe digitale pour soutenir les travailleurs et les entreprises européennes qui sont touchés. Nous devons contrer les arrivées de marchandises destinées au marché américain, mais que l&apos;imposition des tarifs aurait détournées, notamment vers l&apos;Union européenne.</PARA><PARA>Oui, nous devons renforcer nos partenariats avec les autres pays frappés par la guerre commerciale de Trump, mais des partenariats équitables qui ont pour point de départ et pour point d&apos;arrivée les objectifs de développement durable. Il n&apos;est pas question de transiger avec nos droits sociaux et environnementaux ni avec les droits humains. Il n&apos;est donc pas question non plus de se précipiter dans des accords avec la Chine, l&apos;Inde, le Mercosur, qui risqueraient de rendre l&apos;Union européenne encore plus dépendante et vulnérable.</PARA><PARA>Renforcer notre économie stratégique, c&apos;est miser sans délai sur notre indépendance énergétique, notre autonomie alimentaire, l&apos;économie circulaire, la réduction de notre dépendance aux ressources, notre redéploiement industriel, en un seul mot: la transition vers une vraie autonomie européenne.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0040-0000" ACT="2017023910544" PRE="2017023813542" SUIV="2017023910546" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:13:03" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:14:02"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Lynn | Boylan" PP="The Left" LG="EN" MEPID="124984" CODICT="124984"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Lynn Boylan (<PP>The Left</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – <EMPHAS NAME="I">A Uachtaráin</EMPHAS>, Commissioner, when it comes to the EU&apos;s response to Trump&apos;s tariffs, it&apos;s essential that all Member States, including smaller ones like Ireland, are taken into consideration. The collective response must be one that protects workers, that funds and encourages upskilling and that does not pursue the same anti-worker, anti-environment, Trump-lite deregulation agenda.</PARA><PARA>We also cannot exploit this crisis to increase LNG imports or to advance trade deals like Mercosur or the ratification of CETA. Deforestation, food laden with chemicals and corporate courts will not protect workers in Europe, but it will protect the profits of the few. Now is the time for fair, sustainable trade, which does not leave us exposed to the whims of oligarchs or serve the interests of corporates. Instead, it serves the interests of workers and families in Europe.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0041-0000" ACT="2017023910546" PRE="2017023910544" SUIV="2017023910547" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:14:04" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:15:03"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Lukas | Sieper" PP="NI" LG="EN" MEPID="256971" CODICT="256971"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Lukas Sieper (<PP>NI</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, first of all, we are not the group, the Non-attached, that goes against the very nation ...</PARA><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(The President interrupted the speaker)</EMPHAS></PARA><PARA>Sorry. I know, I know, I know. I just wanted to say this. We are not the group.</PARA><PARA>Dear people of Europe, dear Commissioner, in the INTA Committee, you told us: &apos;We will give the US two weeks and then we will respond&apos;. It has been over a month now and the US tariffs are still in place, while we impose our &apos;tactical delay&apos;. That means one of two things: either you lied to this Parliament, which I don&apos;t want to believe, or you don&apos;t know Donald Trump, which I fear is even worse. Maybe I lack the brilliance to grasp the Commission&apos;s plan. But I promise you this: if I don&apos;t understand it, the public doesn&apos;t either.</PARA><PARA>And to those on the left, like Mr Schirdewan, who&apos;s gone, unfortunately: a China that locks up Uyghurs in concentration camps is not our partner, and never can be.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0042-0000" ACT="2017023910547" PRE="2017023910546" SUIV="2017023910548" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:15:00" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:15:33"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="President" PP="NULL" LG="EN" MEPID="125027" CODICT="125027"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">President.</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – I&apos;m going to read the Rules of Procedure: &apos;The Member raising the blue card and the speaker shall not be from the same political group, and they shall not both be non-attached Members.&apos;</PARA><PARA>That is exactly what the Rules say. Remember it for the next time.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0043-0000" ACT="2017023910548" PRE="2017023910547" SUIV="2017023910550" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:15:32" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:16:47"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Eva | Maydell" PP="PPE" LG="EN" MEPID="98341" CODICT="98341"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Eva Maydell (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, Commissioner, dear colleagues, business people know that trade relies on two fundamentals: economic incentive and also trust. When it comes to economic incentives, the numbers in trade volumes between the EU and the US speak for themselves. Just last year, US-EU goods trade hit a record of USD 976 billion.</PARA><PARA>But that trust – trust in rules, commitments, in partners is shaken on both sides of the Atlantic. Economic nationalism does not make you first, but it makes you alone. And this is not leadership – this is volatility masquerading as strength.</PARA><PARA>When we speak about strength, the numbers are clear, and Europe can respond with resolve. But our priority is principled openness, because we are not the Democratic Party: we are an ally.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="IT" INDEX="2-0044-0000" ACT="2017023910550" PRE="2017023910548" SUIV="2017023910552" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:16:51" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:17:59"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Brando | Benifei" PP="S-D" LG="IT" MEPID="124867" CODICT="124867"><LG>IT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Brando Benifei (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Signor Presidente, signor Commissario Šefčovič, onorevoli colleghi, il reale obiettivo dei dazi illegali imposti da Donald Trump è uno e uno solo: stravolgere il modello democratico e sociale europeo, abbattendo le nostre norme che ci tutelano su cosa mangiamo e beviamo, in quale ambiente viviamo, quali diritti abbiamo di fronte ai giganti tecnologici.</PARA><PARA>Da qui dobbiamo mandare un messaggio chiaro: le nostre leggi le decidiamo in Europa per gli europei. Nei prossimi mesi negozieremo per superare questa situazione dannosa per l&apos;economia di entrambe le sponde dell&apos;Atlantico. Con la commissione Commercio saremo a Washington a fine mese. Vogliamo trovare un accordo utile: ma se non ci sarà davvero la volontà di arrivarci, saremo pronti a rispondere con contromisure forti su beni e servizi americani.</PARA><PARA>In ogni caso, l&apos;Europa deve stabilire un&apos;alleanza con tutti coloro che vogliono mantenere un ordine del commercio mondiale fondato sulle regole e stipulare nuovi accordi. Questa che stiamo vivendo è l&apos;ennesima prova: in questo mondo così complicato c&apos;è bisogno di un&apos;Unione europea più unita e più forte.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="HU" INDEX="2-0045-0000" ACT="2017023910552" PRE="2017023910550" SUIV="2017023910554" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:18:02" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:19:29"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Enikő | Győri" PP="PfE" LG="HU" MEPID="96830" CODICT="96830"><LG>HU</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Enikő Győri (<PP>PfE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Elnök Úr! A jelenlegi turbulens időszakban stratégiai nyugalomra van szükség, csak semmi kapkodás, fenyegetőzés. Hideg fejjel át kell gondolni, mi Europa érdeke. Biztos, hogy nem egy kereskedelmi háború! Azzal a saját polgárainknak, vállalatainknak és iparunknak ártanánk a legtöbbet. Sérülnének az ellátó láncok, áremelkedés történne, vállalatokat veszítenénk. Súlyos stratégiai hiba volt, hogy a választások előtt a brüsszeli mainstream egyértelműen letette a voksát a demokrata jelölt mellett. A korrigálás túl későn érkezett. Le kellene végre szokni arról, hogy Brüsszelből próbálják megmondani, egyes országok polgárai milyen kormányra szavazzanak.</PARA><PARA>A Bizottságtól azt várjuk el, hogy hatékony tárgyalással rendezze a kialakult helyzetet. Legyen nyitott az innovatív megoldásokra. Üzletemberrel üzletember módjára kell tárgyalni, közben rendet kell tenni a saját portánkon. Le kell végre építeni a bürokráciát, kevesebb és egyszerűbb szabály kell, véget kell vetni az előző öt év ideológiai, gazdasági és kereskedelmi politikájának, meg kell védeni a gazdákat, és vonzóbbá kell tenni a belső piacot. Így maradhat Európa nyitott mindenki felé a kölcsönös haszon reményében. Csak így nyerhetjük vissza a versenyképességünket, és lehetünk újra komoly szereplői a nemzetközi történéseknek.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="ET" INDEX="2-0046-0000" ACT="2017023910554" PRE="2017023910552" SUIV="2017023910556" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:19:33" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:20:53"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Jaak | Madison" PP="ECR" LG="ET" MEPID="197493" CODICT="197493"><LG>ET</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Jaak Madison (<PP>ECR</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Austatud president! Jah, suur aitäh, head armsad kolleegid! Ja kuidas peaks Euroopa Liit vastama USA tariifidele, mille nad kehtestasid? Ei, me ei peakski Trumpi karistama selle eest, vaid peaksime mõtlema, et kuidas arendada omaenda majandust. Euroopa Liidu praegune majandusruum on direktiivide ja regulatsioonide labürint. See lämmatab ettevõtlikkust, tõrjub investeeringuid ja pidurdab majanduskasvu. Euroopa oli kunagi vabaturumajanduse eestkõneleja, aga on liikumas sotsialistliku käsumajanduse suunas. Ettevõtjad kulutavad praegu rohkem aega regulatiivsete nõuete täitmisele kui toote arendustele. Paljud firmad loobuvad laienemisest, sest ei suuda kanda direktiividest tulenevaid kulusid. Investorid eelistavad oma raha paigutada riikidesse, kus riskid on väiksemad ja regulatsioonid mõistlikumad. Me ei tohi lubada, et bürokraatia asendab vaba ettevõtluse vaimu. Just vabadus on ajalooliselt viinud Euroopa suuremate innovatsioonideni, loonud töökohti ja jõukust. Euroopal on potentsiaal olla juhtiv jõud maailma majanduses, kui ta taastab usu turu vabadusse. See tähendab usaldust ettevõtjate vastu. See tähendab lihtsamaid ja paindlikumaid reegleid. See tähendab vähem direktiive ja rohkem otsustusvabadust. Muu hulgas tähendab see muidugi ka rohepöördele vee peale tõmbamist. Ainult nii kaitseme Euroopa majandushuve ja oma kodanike heaolu.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="FR" INDEX="2-0047-0000" ACT="2017023910556" PRE="2017023910554" SUIV="2017023910558" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:20:55" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:22:06"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Benoit | Cassart" PP="Renew" LG="FR" MEPID="256891" CODICT="256891"><LG>FR</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Benoit Cassart (<PP>Renew</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, le retour de Donald Trump à la Maison-Blanche fait vaciller le multilatéralisme, bouscule les règles du commerce mondial et déstabilise les chaînes d&apos;approvisionnement. Les droits de douane sont devenus des armes économiques. La mondialisation, souvent source indéniable de richesse, est en pleine mutation. La richesse ne ruisselle plus forcément jusqu&apos;aux plus faibles. Le dumping environnemental devient un atout de compétitivité majeur et certains dirigeants politiques ne sont plus fiables.</PARA><PARA>Face à cette dérive, nous devons repenser nos accords commerciaux pour les rendre plus équilibrés, en protégeant nos intérêts vitaux et nos valeurs, et en assurant notre autonomie stratégique. Le commerce international ne se réduit pas à des quotas, à des volumes et à des prix. Il doit retrouver du sens, basé sur la théorie des avantages comparatifs. Il doit redevenir un outil de stabilité qui tire l&apos;humanité vers le haut ainsi qu&apos;un levier de souveraineté.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0048-0000" ACT="2017023910558" PRE="2017023910556" SUIV="2017023910560" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:22:10" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:23:41"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Virginijus | Sinkevičius" PP="Verts/ALE" LG="EN" MEPID="201945" CODICT="201945"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Virginijus Sinkevičius (<PP>Verts/ALE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, dear Minister, dear Commissioner, dear colleagues, the recent US tariffs don&apos;t just hit our exports, they strike at the heart of what should be a fair and trusted partnership. Over EUR 500 billion-worth of EU goods could be affected. Behind that figure, there are real people – our workers, our businesses and the values that we stand for – and the only correct response is with unity, with calm and with purpose.</PARA><PARA>Yes, we have introduced proportionate countermeasures, but we are also keeping the door wide open for a dialogue, for an honest dialogue, offering to boost imports of US goods by EUR 50 billion to help restore balance.</PARA><PARA>Still, this is much more than just a dispute. It&apos;s about Europe shaping its own path – building stronger, more diverse partnerships and standing up for a global trade system based on rules and mutual respect.</PARA><PARA>Across Europe, people also reacted. People are frustrated. Boycotts and anti-American sentiment are rising. But our message is clear. We want solutions, not a trade war. If the US is ready to negotiate, so are we. If not, Europe will stand tall, united, and turn this challenge into an opportunity.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="IT" INDEX="2-0049-0000" ACT="2017023910560" PRE="2017023910558" SUIV="2017023910562" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:23:46" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:25:00"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Pasquale | Tridico" PP="The Left" LG="IT" MEPID="257133" CODICT="257133"><LG>IT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Pasquale Tridico (<PP>The Left</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Signor Presidente, signor Commissario, onorevoli colleghi, la politica commerciale di Trump rispolvera la logica mercantilista secondo cui un disavanzo commerciale rappresenterebbe una minaccia.</PARA><PARA>Nel 2023 gli Stati Uniti hanno importato dall&apos;Unione europea beni per circa 157 miliardi di euro. Però dobbiamo allargare lo sguardo ai servizi e qui notiamo che sono gli Stati Uniti ad avere un surplus di 109 miliardi. Questo ci ricorda di quanto le relazioni economiche siano complesse e vadano lette nel loro insieme.</PARA><PARA>Oggi i dazi sono sospesi ma le tensioni restano e intanto molte grandi aziende statunitensi, in particolare nel digitale, continuano a fare profitti esorbitanti. È una questione di giustizia: dobbiamo mettere riparo a questa situazione. Per questo serve una tassa sui servizi digitali.</PARA><PARA>Inoltre l&apos;Unione europea dovrebbe allargare i suoi legami commerciali con altri paesi emergenti, i BRICS, e non dipendere dalle scelte unilaterali di Trump. Non dimentichiamoci le ricadute economiche dei dazi, la recessione. Per questo dobbiamo puntare anche sulla crescita dei salari, sulla domanda interna e sui consumi. L&apos;Europa deve vincere le sfide con maggiore forza nei confronti del potente di turno a Washington.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0050-0000" ACT="2017023910562" PRE="2017023910560" SUIV="2017023910564" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:25:04" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:26:50"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Željana | Zovko" PP="PPE" LG="EN" MEPID="185341" CODICT="185341"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Željana Zovko (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, dear colleagues, war begins in the minds of the people, and it&apos;s in their minds that peace is also created. For decades, we relied heavily on American partners, and we still do for our defence and defence of our trade routes, at least in the Red Sea.</PARA><PARA>But with unjustified imposition of tariffs, it has become clear we must take matters in our own hands and strengthen our competitiveness. We need to simplify it and we need to work and to attract investments.</PARA><PARA>We now have a 90-day tariff pause. This is not the time to wait. It&apos;s a window of opportunity, a chance to negotiate the best possible outcome for both sides of the Atlantic; an outcome that allows business to thrive, to support millions of jobs; an outcome that strengthens, not harms, our economies; one that reinforces the largest trading partnership in the world.</PARA><PARA>In an era of free trade and the rules-based global order, there is no room for protectionism. Protectionism comes at a cost, a cost that must not be borne by any single industry or country alone.</PARA><PARA>A change in US administration should not mean a change in the fundamental strength of our transatlantic relationship. One thing must remain clear: the United States has always been and will remain our strongest partner and ally, not one-party regimes or autocracies.</PARA><PARA>The European Union must continue with the calm logic that has made us the strongest single market in the world – the logic that allows small fish to survive in turbulent waters where large fish prey.</PARA><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(The speaker agreed to take a blue-card question)</EMPHAS></PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="LT" INDEX="2-0051-0000" ACT="2017023910564" PRE="2017023910562" SUIV="2017023910567" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:26:57" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:28:15"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Petras | Gražulis" PP="ESN" LG="LT" MEPID="256808" CODICT="256808"><LG>LT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Petras Gražulis (<PP>ESN</PP>), </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">pakėlus mėlynąją kortelę pateiktas klausimas</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Kaip čia ir kalbėjo kolegos, Briuselis ir ne tik Briuselis per prezidento rinkimus aktyviai palaikė demokratų kandidatą ir žemino trumpą. Dabar taip pat Europos Sąjunga labiau negu Putiną žemina Trumpą ... (posėdžio pirmininkas nutraukė ir paprašė pradėti iš naujo). Gerbiama pranešėja, čia kalbėjo prieš tai kandidatai, diskutantai, kad Europos Sąjunga ir Briuselis per prezidento rinkimus Amerikoje palaikė demokratų kandidatą. Iš Trumpo nemažai tyčiojosi. Išrinktas prezidentas Trumpas dabar taip pat susilaukia nemažai patyčių iš Europos Sąjungos, net ir vadovų, ypač iš žiniasklaidos. Jis tapo skaitant žiniasklaidą pavojingesnis negu Putinas. Klausykit, ar jūs nežadate atsiprašyti Trumpo ir Amerikos? Ir tik tokiu atveju prasidės normalūs santykiai. Ką jūs galvojate?</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0052-0000" ACT="2017023910567" PRE="2017023910564" SUIV="2017023910569" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:28:16" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:29:01"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Željana | Zovko" PP="PPE" LG="EN" MEPID="185341" CODICT="185341"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Željana Zovko (<PP>PPE</PP>), </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">blue-card answer</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – As a politician, I could just say that every politician and everyone in this House has responsibility for the words they say. So, I never insulted anyone. It&apos;s not mine to speak on behalf of other politicians.</PARA><PARA>Democratic words should be preserved to build peace, and not war with words. This was the beginning of my speech as well. So, I stick to the logic that there is no place for insults in politics.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EL" INDEX="2-0053-0000" ACT="2017023910569" PRE="2017023910567" SUIV="2017023910571" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:29:06" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:30:23"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Γιάννης | Μανιάτης" PP="S-D" LG="EL" MEPID="256824" CODICT="256824"><LG>EL</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Γιάννης Μανιάτης (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η απόφαση Trump για επιβολή δασμών 20% σε ευρωπαϊκά προϊόντα και ο εμπορικός πόλεμος ανταλλαγών ύψους ενός τρισεκατομμυρίου ευρώ θα επηρεάσουν αρνητικά τόσο την Ευρώπη όσο και τις Ηνωμένες Πολιτείες. Παρά την αναβολή τους μέχρι τον Ιούλιο, έχουν ήδη αρχίσει να εφαρμόζονται δασμοί ύψους 10%, ενώ παραμένουν οι δασμοί 25% σε αλουμίνιο, χάλυβα και αυτοκίνητα.</PARA><PARA>Η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση θα πρέπει να αξιοποιήσει το διάστημα μέχρι τον Ιούλιο, ώστε να διαπραγματευτεί μια συμφωνία που θα αντιμετωπίζει όλα τα εμπορικά εμπόδια και από τις δύο πλευρές του Ατλαντικού. Την ίδια στιγμή, όμως, θα πρέπει να ετοιμαζόμαστε και για το ενδεχόμενο να μην υπάρξει συμφωνία. Σε αυτή την περίπτωση, πρέπει ενωμένοι οι Ευρωπαίοι να αποφασίσουμε για μια σειρά από αντίμετρα.</PARA><PARA>Επιπλέον, απαιτούνται μέτρα οικονομικής ενίσχυσης των παραγωγών μας που πλήττονται από τους δασμούς, ιδιαίτερα στον αγροδιατροφικό τομέα —για παράδειγμα, στην Ελλάδα, των παραγωγών επιτραπέζιας ελιάς και των παραγωγών ροδάκινου. Δεν πρέπει να αφήσουμε τους παραγωγούς και τη βιομηχανία μας να πληρώσουν το τίμημα ενός παράλογου εμπορικού πολέμου.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="IT" INDEX="2-0054-0000" ACT="2017023910571" PRE="2017023910569" SUIV="2017023910573" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:30:29" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:31:49"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Isabella | Tovaglieri" PP="PfE" LG="IT" MEPID="197580" CODICT="197580"><LG>IT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Isabella Tovaglieri (<PP>PfE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, mentre l&apos;Europa tratta sui dazi, i dazi sono già tra noi. E non li ha messi Trump: li avete messi voi in questi anni, quando avete tagliato le gambe alla manifattura, al commercio, all&apos;agricoltura, con oneri burocratici che costano alle nostre imprese ogni anno 154 miliardi di euro, quindi molto più dei 100 miliardi di euro in cui sono stati stimati i futuribili dazi americani.</PARA><PARA>Vi siete autoimposti i dazi anche quando avete varato miopi politiche ideologiche come il <EMPHAS NAME="I">Green Deal</EMPHAS>, lo stop ai motori endotermici che stanno solo portando l&apos;Europa alla desertificazione produttiva e alla disoccupazione, privando le famiglie del loro potere d&apos;acquisto.</PARA><PARA>Quindi, anziché puntare il dito contro quei leader che scelgono di fare l&apos;interesse del proprio paese, prendete esempio e cancellate tutte quelle imposizioni che stanno portando l&apos;Europa al suicidio industriale e geopolitico.</PARA><PARA>Altrimenti i dazi sono l&apos;ennesimo comodo capro espiatorio per coprire i fallimenti delle politiche autolesioniste, incapaci di dare un futuro all&apos;Europa: il futuro che merita.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0055-0000" ACT="2017023910573" PRE="2017023910571" SUIV="2017023910575" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:31:55" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:33:08"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Rihards | Kols" PP="ECR" LG="EN" MEPID="220871" CODICT="220871"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Rihards Kols (<PP>ECR</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, dear colleagues, the US tariffs are harsh, but they remind us how critical it is to deepen, not weaken, our transatlantic bond. In a world of fast-moving competition, while we debate, others – especially authoritarian regimes – are moving fast to dominate emerging technologies and critical raw materials.</PARA><PARA>This is the time to align. We need permanent EU trade representation not just in Washington but in the wider US, to identify, negotiate and remove the barriers that still hold back transatlantic trade. But we must do so without compromising our standards: food, safety, security, etc.</PARA><PARA>Targeted coordination on critical sectors and technologies is what we should be locking in on. That includes improving customs processing, eliminating red tape, and other measures that slow innovation on both sides of the Atlantic.</PARA><PARA>And while I rarely quote Elon Musk, I&apos;ll agree with him on this: Europe and the US should aim for a &apos;zero-tariff zone&apos;. So a stronger, freer trade relationship – rooted in trust and common democratic ground – is in both of our interests.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="SK" INDEX="2-0056-0000" ACT="2017023910575" PRE="2017023910573" SUIV="2017023910577" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:33:13" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:34:31"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Ľubica | Karvašová" PP="Renew" LG="SK" MEPID="257013" CODICT="257013"><LG>SK</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Ľubica Karvašová (<PP>Renew</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Vážený pán predsedajúci, Trump Američanom odkázal, že na Vianoce bude menej hračiek a budú drahšie. To sú skvelé výsledky politiky ciel Donalda Trumpa. Politikov, čo mu fandia, ale máme aj v Európe a aj na Slovensku na čele s predsedom vlády Róbertom Ficom. Naši občania pritom budú trpieť najviac: v automobilkách, oceliarniach, v subdodávkach. Vláda sa má za naše firmy biť aj za našich občanov, a to spolu s Úniou. Nestačí zamestnancov poslať na kurzarbeit. A nepomôže ani cesta premiéra do Moskvy tento týždeň. Je dobré, že v Kanade aj v Austrálii vyhrali politici, ktorí veria vo férový obchod a nie v šikanu. Máme otvárať trhy, máme zlepšovať podnikateľské prostredie, máme lákať firmy a talenty do Európy. Ale áno, treba aj rokovať a trpezlivo rokovať so Spojenými štátmi. Ale aj my chceme spravodlivosť v obchode. Obrovskí digitálni obri a giganty v Európe zarábajú miliardy eur. Je to fér? Ak sa nedohodneme so Spojenými štátmi, Komisia musí konať a my budeme jej partnermi.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="ES" INDEX="2-0057-0000" ACT="2017023910577" PRE="2017023910575" SUIV="2017023910579" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:34:35" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:35:46"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Vicent | Marzà Ibáñez" PP="Verts/ALE" LG="ES" MEPID="257016" CODICT="257016"><LG>ES</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Vicent Marzà Ibáñez (<PP>Verts/ALE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Señor presidente, señor comisario, las políticas arancelarias de Trump no son una guerra comercial. Son, sobre todo, un ataque a nuestros valores y a nuestra democracia. Es una lucha entre la oligarquía y los demócratas. Lo hemos visto en dos episodios recientemente.</PARA><PARA>Primero, se ha hecho patente con el rechazo a la propuesta del comisario de generar un espacio de cero aranceles entre Europa y Estados Unidos, así como con el rechazo a la visita del ministro español de Economía, que terminó con una crítica directa a los impuestos que tenemos en la Unión Europea, una crítica directa a nuestra protección social, medioambiental y laboral.</PARA><PARA>Por eso le pedimos, señor comisario, que no ceda al chantaje, que refuerce a nuestros trabajadores y trabajadoras y nuestra economía, que refuerce nuestra legislación medioambiental y ―sobre todo― que deje de pactar con el caballo de Troya de la Administración Trump aquí en Europa, que es la extrema derecha que nos quiere más débiles y más divididos.</PARA><PARA>Por ello, le decimos alto y claro que no ceda al chantaje y que nuestros valores y nuestra democracia no están en venta.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0058-0000" ACT="2017023910579" PRE="2017023910577" SUIV="2017023910581" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:35:51" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:37:03"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Li | Andersson" PP="The Left" LG="EN" MEPID="256805" CODICT="256805"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Li Andersson (<PP>The Left</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, the US is ruled by an authoritarian president who is using trade policies as a means of coercion and political extortion. While it is clear that European workers will only lose in a full-fledged trade war, the EU should be much bolder and much more imaginative in its own response to Trump&apos;s actions.</PARA><PARA>The EU should target the oligarchs that are close to Trump, through action directed at Tesla and Musk, and by digital tax aimed at the huge digital platforms. The EU should also signal its readiness to use the Anti-Coercion Instrument.</PARA><PARA>But most importantly, we need to make the European economy less dependent on US exports. That means supporting internal demand in the European markets, and that means supporting real wage growth and also increasing investments. More than ever, we need to put people and workers first in our economic policymaking.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="DE" INDEX="2-0059-0000" ACT="2017023910581" PRE="2017023910579" SUIV="2017023910583" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:37:05" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:38:16"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Angelika | Niebler" PP="PPE" LG="DE" MEPID="4289" CODICT="4289"><LG>DE</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Angelika Niebler (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Herr Präsident, Herr Vizepräsident, Herr Minister, liebe Kolleginnen, liebe Kollegen! US‑Zölle treffen unsere Unternehmen ins Mark. Die Vereinigten Staaten sind unser wichtigster Handelspartner, und viele Arbeitsplätze hängen hier in der Europäischen Union am Export. Wenn die US‑Administration einseitig unberechtigt Zölle verhängt und uns damit letztlich den Zollkrieg erklärt, müssen wir entschlossen und vor allen Dingen gemeinsam handeln.</PARA><PARA>Ich finde, dass die Kommission richtig reagiert hat – besonnen: Sie haben nicht sofort Gegenzölle verhängt, Sie waren immer zum Dialog bereit, für Verhandlungen offen, haben hart verhandelt. Aber die Kommission hat sich auch vorbereitet, Gegenmaßnahmen zu verhängen, sofort zu reagieren, falls die Zölle scharf gestellt werden.</PARA><PARA>Ich denke, es ist wichtig, daneben auch neue strategische Partner zu finden. Auch da muss ich der Kommission ein Kompliment aussprechen. Sie sind in der ganzen Welt unterwegs: Mercosur‑Abkommen ist abgeschlossen worden, mit Indien wird verhandelt, mit den ASEAN‑Staaten, mit afrikanischen Ländern. Ich begrüße alle diese Initiativen – das ist genau der richtige Weg – und bedanke mich und wünsche, dass Sie so weitermachen und erfolgreich auch weitere Handelsabkommen abschließen können.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="IT" INDEX="2-0060-0000" ACT="2017023910583" PRE="2017023910581" SUIV="2017023910585" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:38:23" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:39:43"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Camilla | Laureti" PP="S-D" LG="IT" MEPID="230085" CODICT="230085"><LG>IT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Camilla Laureti (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, spesso quando si parla di guerre commerciali si mette l&apos;accento sull&apos;aggettivo &quot;commerciale&quot; ma bisogna metterlo sul sostantivo &quot;guerre&quot;: queste sono le parole chiare e nette del Presidente Mattarella. Un monito a non dimenticare la storia che ha dimostrato come l&apos;ostilità commerciale possa portare a scontri ancora più gravi.</PARA><PARA>I dazi hanno già cominciato a fare danni prima che Trump li firmasse e poi li sospendesse per 90 giorni: imprese e lavoratori lamentano situazioni drammatiche con merci bloccate nei porti, anche a causa dell&apos;incertezza.</PARA><PARA>Novanta giorni è il tempo che ci è stato dato per mettere in campo una risposta che deve essere compatta, europea, per sventare una guerra commerciale che avrebbe conseguenze enormi per le nostre esportazioni, soprattutto nel settore agroalimentare, che nel 2024 ha toccato quota 30 miliardi di euro.</PARA><PARA>I dazi colpiscono settori strategici come quello dell&apos;agricoltura, fatta di prodotti di qualità e rispetto al quale è centrale il ruolo rivestito dal <EMPHAS NAME="I">made in Italy</EMPHAS>. Tutelano invece prodotti di minore qualità.</PARA><PARA>La posta in gioco è troppo alta: non possiamo permetterci divisioni e frammentazioni. Siamo ad un tornante della storia delicata e da come lo attraverseremo dipenderà il nostro futuro.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="NL" INDEX="2-0061-0000" ACT="2017023910585" PRE="2017023910583" SUIV="2017023910587" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:39:48" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:41:06"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Sebastian | Kruis" PP="PfE" LG="NL" MEPID="256996" CODICT="256996"><LG>NL</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Sebastian Kruis (<PP>PfE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Voorzitter, allereerst wil ik commissaris Šefčovič bedanken voor zijn inzet om de handelsrelaties tussen de Europese Unie en de Verenigde Staten te verbeteren. Ik ben ook blij dat hij mijn voorstel om te streven naar wederzijdse 0 %-tarieven heeft overgenomen. Toch zien we dat, terwijl de commissaris probeert de plooien glad te strijken in onze handelsrelaties, er elders zand in de machine wordt gegooid. Zo legde Brussel vorige week opnieuw boetes op aan Amerikaanse techbedrijven, deze keer aan Meta en Apple.</PARA><PARA>De Verenigde Staten hebben al eerder aangegeven dat zij dergelijke boetes beschouwen als economische barrières, die net zo schadelijk zijn als tarieven. Mijn vraag is dan ook: is het niet contraproductief dat Brussel met de ene hand onderhandelt over het afschaffen van tarieven en met de andere boetes uitdeelt die Washington als nieuwe tarieven beschouwt? Hoe denkt de commissaris dat dit kan bijdragen aan het sluiten van een goede deal?</PARA><PARA>Laten we stoppen met het laten gijzelen van ons handelsbeleid door linkse partijen die, na hun herhaalde verlies bij de verkiezingen, plotseling een obsessie lijken te hebben ontwikkeld voor het straffen van grote techbedrijven. Handelsakkoorden bouw je immers met bruggen, niet met boetes. Laten we dus kiezen voor groei in plaats van ideologische vendetta&apos;s.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="NL" INDEX="2-0062-0000" ACT="2017023910587" PRE="2017023910585" SUIV="2017023910589" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:41:10" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:42:24"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Kris | Van Dijck" PP="ECR" LG="NL" MEPID="256884" CODICT="256884"><LG>NL</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Kris Van Dijck (<PP>ECR</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Voorzitter, de aankondiging van de Amerikaanse president over de nieuwe handelstarieven heeft wereldwijd onmiskenbaar een grote schokgolf veroorzaakt, ook hier in de EU. We zijn in korte tijd geëvolueerd van een op regels gebaseerd handelsbeleid naar een handelsbeleid dat gebaseerd is op macht en dat schaamteloos wordt gebruikt als pressiemiddel.</PARA><PARA>Ik roep de Commissie op om vooral het hoofd koel te houden en constructief en zelfverzekerd te onderhandelen. Zoals reeds aangehaald, zijn een nul-voor-nultarief op industriële goederen en een snelle douaneafhandeling een win-win voor beide partijen.</PARA><PARA>Bovenal mogen we ons als EU niet uit elkaar laten spelen of zelf ondoordacht te hoge muren optrekken. Laat ons één zaak niet vergeten: zowel vanuit historisch als economisch oogpunt komen hoge handelstarieven altijd als een boemerang terug naar afzender. Laat ons dat voorkomen.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0063-0000" ACT="2017023910589" PRE="2017023910587" SUIV="2017023910591" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:42:29" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:43:56"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Barry | Cowen" PP="Renew" LG="EN" MEPID="257297" CODICT="257297"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Barry Cowen (<PP>Renew</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, since the election of President Trump, I&apos;ve constantly pointed out that the economic bond between Europe and the US is one of the strongest globally and of great mutual benefit – a relationship that tariffs, of course, will only damage. That is why I&apos;ve repeatedly called for a strategic, measured and politically precise response to President Trump.</PARA><PARA>I am satisfied that the Commission has so far reflected this, consulting Member States from drafting its counter tariff list and rightly deferring action following the 90-day delay to give diplomacy a chance. But should this pause end without substantive US engagement, we must be ready to respond firmly, proportionately, and as one.</PARA><PARA>At the same time, this uncertainty in EU-US trade has brought the urgent need to broaden our trade partnerships into sharper focus, but not at the expense of certain countries or sectors. For Ireland, where agriculture remains a vital pillar of our economy, that means ensuring the fair treatment of our farmers in any future agreement. Proposed deals, including that with the Mercosur bloc, must reflect EU values of fairness and reciprocity. As it stands, that deal unfortunately does not meet that standard.</PARA><PARA>In the days and weeks ahead, I urge the Commission to remember that Europe&apos;s strength lies not in noise or brashness, but in unity, resolve, and staying power. We learned that through the COVID-19 pandemic, through Brexit and the financial crash, and I have no doubt that, once again, we will stay the course.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="SV" INDEX="2-0064-0000" ACT="2017023910591" PRE="2017023910589" SUIV="2017023910593" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:44:03" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:45:18"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Isabella | Lövin" PP="Verts/ALE" LG="SV" MEPID="96675" CODICT="96675"><LG>SV</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Isabella Lövin (<PP>Verts/ALE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Herr talman! Donald Trumps tullar är skadliga för hela världen, inte minst för de allra fattigaste, för amerikanerna själva. De är baserade på siffror som är tagna helt ur luften. Syftet tycks vara att destabilisera världen och utmana den regelbaserade världsordningen.</PARA><PARA>Men människor världen över vill inte detta. Det visar också valen i Kanada och Australien nyligen. I båda länderna vann partier som tydligt sagt nej till splittring. I stället har man valt ledare som står upp för samarbete och som står upp för den internationella världsordningens spelregler och rättvisa handelsrelationer. Det här är viktiga signaler och det är en påminnelse om att en annan väg är möjlig. Det är just den vägen vi måste hålla fast vid.EU måste fortsätta att stärka banden med likasinnade länder.</PARA><PARA>I ett handelskrig finns det inga vinnare, bara vanliga människor som får betala mer för mindre. Därför måste EU stå upp för den rimlighet och det ansvarstagande som Trump-administrationen saknar.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="PT" INDEX="2-0065-0000" ACT="2017023910593" PRE="2017023910591" SUIV="2017023910595" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:45:24" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:46:33"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Lídia | Pereira" PP="PPE" LG="PT" MEPID="197738" CODICT="197738"><LG>PT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Lídia Pereira (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Senhor Presidente, Donald Trump transformou os Estados Unidos no país do pisca-pisca. Hoje sim, amanhã não, e depois ninguém sabe o que se segue. Mas, no meio de tanta instabilidade e incerteza, há um dado adquirido: o mundo mudou, e a relação transatlântica não voltará a ser a mesma.</PARA><PARA>Cabe-nos, por isso, reagir com unidade, mas também com visão estratégica. Não nos esqueçamos de que somos uma potência comercial. Temos de agir como tal. Hoje, a diversificação de mercados não é uma opção; é mesmo uma urgência. Mas temos de ser rápidos.</PARA><PARA>Dou um exemplo: passaram cinco meses desde a assinatura do acordo Mercosul, que ainda está em fase de revisão jurídica e tradução nas línguas oficiais de cada Estado-Membro. Se queremos proteger o nosso mercado, a nossa indústria, os nossos empregos, temos de ser mais eficazes, porque, num mundo onde todos estão a disputar os mesmos mercados, quem chega tarde perde — e a Europa não pode perder.</PARA><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(A oradora aceita responder a uma pergunta «cartão azul»)</EMPHAS></PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="PT" INDEX="2-0066-0000" ACT="2017023910595" PRE="2017023910593" SUIV="2017023910597" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:46:42" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:47:31"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="João | Oliveira" PP="The Left" LG="PT" MEPID="257083" CODICT="257083"><LG>PT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">João Oliveira (<PP>The Left</PP>), </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">Pergunta segundo o procedimento «cartão azul»</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Senhor Presidente, Senhora Deputada Lídia Pereira, falou na necessidade da diversificação de mercados e de uma política comercial mais alargada. Essa é, infelizmente, uma das competências que foram transferidas para a União Europeia e em que os Estados nacionais não têm hoje qualquer possibilidade de desenvolvimento da sua ação — o caso de Portugal é um exemplo flagrante disso.</PARA><PARA>Mas a pergunta que lhe quero fazer tem que ver com outra dimensão: a Senhora Deputada não considera que mais importante ainda é a dinamização do mercado interno, aumentando o poder de compra, aumentando salários e pensões, para que, com a dinamização do mercado interno, fiquemos menos vulneráveis e menos expostos às consequências que têm decisões como aquelas que Donald Trump tem tomado nos Estados Unidos? Não acha que devia ser esse o caminho que se devia fazer, nomeadamente em Portugal, ao contrário daquilo que o atual governo PSD-CDS tem feito?</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="PT" INDEX="2-0067-0000" ACT="2017023910597" PRE="2017023910595" SUIV="2017023910599" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:47:29" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:48:24"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Lídia | Pereira" PP="PPE" LG="PT" MEPID="197738" CODICT="197738"><LG>PT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Lídia Pereira (<PP>PPE</PP>), </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">Resposta segundo o procedimento «cartão azul»</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Muito obrigada, Senhor Deputado, pela pergunta. Se por mercado interno se está a referir ao mercado interno europeu, eu não poderia concordar mais. Nós temos mesmo de trabalhar no sentido de remover todas as barreiras que ainda existem, todos os obstáculos que ainda existem ao comércio dentro das fronteiras da União Europeia.</PARA><PARA>Portanto, sim, só assim é que vamos estar com capacidade de responder de forma robusta àquilo que são as aspirações e os anseios das nossas empresas, não só portuguesas, mas as empresas europeias, para que ganhem escala, para que possam competir a nível internacional.</PARA><PARA>Portanto, eu creio que sim. Essas falhas estão identificadas já em vários relatórios, não só no relatório de Mario Draghi, mas também de Enrico Letta, em que nós temos também trabalho de casa para fazer e, portanto, a estratégia passa por, sim, diversificar os nossos mercados no comércio internacional, e sim, eliminar as barreiras que ainda existem no mercado interno europeu.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="ES" INDEX="2-0068-0000" ACT="2017023910599" PRE="2017023910597" SUIV="2017023910601" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:48:28" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:49:43"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Javier | Moreno Sánchez" PP="S-D" LG="ES" MEPID="28347" CODICT="28347"><LG>ES</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Javier Moreno Sánchez (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Señor presidente, señor comisario, señor ministro, la nueva Administración americana nos ha situado ante una guerra comercial preocupante y sin sentido en la que perdemos todos y en la que ganarán, si no los detenemos, la inflación, el desempleo y la recesión. Se abrirán paso el unilateralismo, la autocracia y la pobreza.</PARA><PARA>Señor comisario, en estos noventa días hay que negociar de igual a igual, con la seguridad que supone ser el mayor bloque comercial y el mayor mercado interior del mundo. Al tiempo, tenemos que preparar medidas proporcionales de contraataque y planes de apoyo a los sectores que puedan verse afectados por los aranceles, como lo ha hecho el Gobierno de Pedro Sánchez en España, con más de 14 000 millones de euros. Espero que el Partido Popular se ponga del lado de nuestra ciudadanía, de nuestros trabajadores y de nuestras empresas y voten el plan esta semana.</PARA><PARA>Finalmente, tenemos que diversificar nuestras relaciones con socios como Japón, China, Vietnam, Canadá, Mercosur o México, entre otros, y utilizar nuestro <EMPHAS NAME="I">soft power</EMPHAS> para convertirnos en baluarte mundial del multilateralismo, la democracia y la legalidad internacional.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="DE" INDEX="2-0069-0000" ACT="2017023910601" PRE="2017023910599" SUIV="2017023910603" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:50:05" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:51:25"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Petra | Steger" PP="PfE" LG="DE" MEPID="220897" CODICT="220897"><LG>DE</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Petra Steger (<PP>PfE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Herr Präsident, sehr geehrte Damen und Herren! Es ist wirklich erstaunlich, wie Sie Europa wirklich in allen Bereichen regelrecht gegen die Wand fahren und sich noch immer hier hinstellen und mit Ihrer moralischen Abgehobenheit mit dem Finger immer auf die bösen anderen zeigen. Nein, nicht erst seit Trump seine Zollpolitik gestartet hat, geht es mit der Wettbewerbsfähigkeit der Wirtschaft und dem Wohlstand in Europa stetig bergab. Daran ist Europa schon ganz alleine schuld. Während die USA entschlossen ihre wirtschaftlichen Interessen durchsetzen, belasten Sie die Unternehmen immer mehr und noch mehr. Stichwort <EMPHAS NAME="I">Green Deal –</EMPHAS> <EMPHAS NAME="I">Green Disaster</EMPHAS> –, Sanktionen, Geldschwemmepolitik, Energiepolitik, Lieferkettengesetz, Emissionszertifikatehandel, Verbrenner-Aus, Grenzausgleichsmechanismus, Bürokratie, Überregulierung und, und, und. Wir erleben die größte Deindustrialisierung Europas. Und was ist die Strategie der Europäischen Union? Nichts.</PARA><PARA>Sie kritisieren die USA für ihre Zollpolitik. Dabei waren Sie es selbst, die vorher auch schon Zölle zum Beispiel gegen China verhängt haben. Ihre Heuchelei und Doppelmoral schreit zum Himmel. Eins drauf legt nur noch die Verliererampel in Österreich, die Österreich in einen Pleitestaat verwandelt und dafür sorgt, dass wir die stärkste Rezession aller EU‑Länder haben. Die EU wollte der innovativste Wirtschaftsraum der Welt werden. Davon sind wir heute weit entfernt. Während China und die USA die Zukunft erfinden, macht Europa nur eins: regulieren.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="RO" INDEX="2-0070-0000" ACT="2017023910603" PRE="2017023910601" SUIV="2017023910605" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:51:28" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:52:49"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Adrian-George | Axinia" PP="ECR" LG="RO" MEPID="257117" CODICT="257117"><LG>RO</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Adrian-George Axinia (<PP>ECR</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Domnule președinte, stimați colegi, îmi revine bucuria să vă anunț că primul tur al alegerilor prezidențiale din România a fost câștigat detașat de candidatul conservator George Simion, președintele formațiunii politice din care fac parte. Simion este un proamerican convins, dar și un om care își dorește o Europă puternică și reformată. În ceea ce privește această isterie a taxelor vamale, care a născut atâtea vituperații de la acest pupitru, eu vă spun că ceea ce face administrația republicană de la Washington este să ne trezească la realitate – asta pentru că mașina numită Europa derapează grav, cu niște conducători adormiți la volan.</PARA><PARA>Acest război al taxelor vamale ne arată trei lucruri. În primul rând, că avem impozite și taxe prea mari în Europa; de aceea am sugrumat inițiativa privată și de aceea companiile europene și-au pierdut din competitivitate și nu mai reușesc să inoveze. În al doilea rând, că avem nevoie de restartarea industriei europene. Trebuie să începem să producem din nou aici cele necesare dezvoltării țărilor noastre, să nu ne mai bazăm atât de ușor pe importuri de bunuri de consum foarte ieftine. Și, nu în ultimul rând, că măsurile de răzbunare propuse de Comisia Europeană sunt penibile și nu există vreo strategie de negociere. Americanii pun taxe pe oțel și automobile, iar Bruxelles-ul vrea taxe pe whisky și Harley-Davidson.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="FR" INDEX="2-0071-0000" ACT="2017023910605" PRE="2017023910603" SUIV="2017023910607" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:52:52" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:54:16"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Marie-Pierre | Vedrenne" PP="Renew" LG="FR" MEPID="197502" CODICT="197502"><LG>FR</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Marie-Pierre Vedrenne (<PP>Renew</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Ministre, Monsieur le Commissaire, presque aucun pays n&apos;est épargné, aucun secteur à l&apos;abri. L&apos;idéologie rôde dans les couloirs de la Maison-Blanche de Donald Trump, un protectionnisme brutal, assumé, sans règles ni limites. Certains, ici, embarrassés, peinent à cacher un fond de satisfaction. Leur projet devient réalité, appliqué avec zèle par une administration étrangère. D&apos;autres voudraient nous entraîner dans une escalade sans fin: droits de douane contre droits de douane, barrières commerciales contre barrières commerciales.</PARA><PARA>L&apos;Union européenne, forte et unie, a choisi une autre voie, celle d&apos;une riposte ciblée, proportionnée, suspendue, à ce stade, pour ne jamais rester opposée au dialogue. Monsieur le Commissaire, je vous soutiendrai tant que vous défendrez avec clarté et fermeté la prospérité internationale et les intérêts européens, et tant que vous serez prêt à utiliser tous les instruments que nous avons façonnés ensemble.</PARA><PARA>Les choix protectionnistes américains constituent une opportunité, celle d&apos;approfondir notre politique industrielle européenne avec des investissements massifs, mais aussi de renforcer des partenariats, de diversifier nos alliances pour enfin bâtir un ordre économique stable, juste et durable.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="PL" INDEX="2-0072-0000" ACT="2017023910607" PRE="2017023910605" SUIV="2017023910609" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:54:22" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:55:40"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Bogdan Andrzej | Zdrojewski" PP="PPE" LG="PL" MEPID="124893" CODICT="124893"><LG>PL</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Bogdan Andrzej Zdrojewski (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Panie Przewodniczący! Panie Komisarzu! Panie Ministrze! Wszyscy doskonale wiemy, że decyzje dotyczące podatków, w tym ceł, nie powinny zapadać z dnia na dzień. Nie powinny być wdrażane z dnia na dzień. Doskonale wiemy, że większość przedmiotów, towarów powstaje nie w cyklach dziennych. Powstaje w bardzo skomplikowanym łańcuchu produkcji przez podmioty gospodarcze. Te podmioty gospodarcze oczekują, krótko mówiąc, stabilności. One kalkulują, liczą, szacują swoje koszty. Przedmioty też nie poruszają się w świecie z prędkością światła. Są transportowane taką lub inną drogą, ale to wymaga czasu, cierpliwości, pewnych kosztów. Główny więc dzisiaj apel jest o to, aby wszystkie takie decyzje zapadały z odpowiednim wyprzedzeniem, aby nie zapadały z dnia na dzień, aby nie powodowały druzgocących efektów, jeżeli chodzi o kalkulacje ekonomiczne.</PARA><PARA>Przy tej okazji jedno podziękowanie. Kończy się polska prezydencja. Byłem dumny z niej jak byłem ministrem. Jestem dumny z niej w chwili obecnej. Chciałem panu ministrowi Adamowi Szłapce bardzo podziękować za stałą, adekwatną obecność na wszystkich naszych sesjach. Będziemy mieli jeszcze jedną w Strasburgu, a potem będziemy trzymać kciuki za prezydencję duńską. Wszystkiego dobrego!</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="FR" INDEX="2-0073-0000" ACT="2017023910609" PRE="2017023910607" SUIV="2017023910611" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:55:45" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:56:57"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Raphaël | Glucksmann" PP="S-D" LG="FR" MEPID="197694" CODICT="197694"><LG>FR</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Raphaël Glucksmann (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, le président des États-Unis est un «bully» qui voit le monde comme une cour de récréation et, face à un «bully», baisser les yeux ne sert à rien. Espérer passer entre les gouttes ne sert à rien non plus. Il faut montrer que l&apos;Europe est forte.</PARA><PARA>Alors plutôt qu&apos;une approche classique, «tu taxes mon vin, je taxe ton whisky», une approche qui serait trop coûteuse pour nos entreprises et trop prévisible pour dissuader Trump, montrons que nous sommes prêts à cibler, le cas échéant, le cœur de sa puissance: les services digitaux américains, les piliers de la fameuse «broligarchie» trumpiste. En utilisant enfin la force de notre marché, appliquons nos lois sur le numérique, œuvrons ensemble à des alternatives européennes souveraines aux Amazon, Facebook, X et consorts.</PARA><PARA>Le moment historique que nous traversons est celui de l&apos;émergence en matière de commerce, de défense ou d&apos;industrie d&apos;une puissance européenne souveraine. Une puissance dont l&apos;acte de naissance même est aussi un acte de divorce. Le choix que nous ferons maintenant définira la nature de l&apos;Europe pour les décennies à venir. Le statu quo est impossible, alors il vous faut aller de l&apos;avant.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="FR" INDEX="2-0074-0000" ACT="2017023910611" PRE="2017023910609" SUIV="2017023910613" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:57:02" VOD-END="2025-05-06T10:58:53"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Jean-Paul | Garraud" PP="PfE" LG="FR" MEPID="197628" CODICT="197628"><LG>FR</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Jean-Paul Garraud (<PP>PfE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Monsieur le Président, cela fait un mois que les États-Unis imposent une surtaxe de 25 % sur les importations de voitures européennes. C&apos;est un véritable coup de massue pour notre industrie automobile, déjà exposée à une sévère concurrence asiatique. Ce n&apos;est ni un accident ni une surprise, Donald Trump avait clairement annoncé ses intentions; mais c&apos;est surtout la conséquence directe de décennies d&apos;absence de protectionnisme européen et d&apos;ouverture de nos marchés à la terre entière.</PARA><PARA>Sous couvert de transition écologique, la Commission européenne a détruit l&apos;essentiel de nos filières industrielles, sacrifié nos motorisations thermiques, imposé de nombreuses normes destructrices et livré notre avenir automobile à la Chine sur l&apos;autel du mondialisme et du tout électrique. Pendant que les États-Unis et Pékin protègent leurs industries, Bruxelles subventionne à coups de milliards des ONG militantes responsables d&apos;une propagande anti-voiture. Pire encore, la Commission vient de proposer l&apos;instauration d&apos;un contrôle technique annuel obligatoire pour les véhicules de plus de dix ans et pour tous les automobilistes européens. Il s&apos;agit d&apos;une mesure punitive, injuste et injustifiée techniquement, qui ne vise qu&apos;à culpabiliser, taxer et dissuader nos concitoyens d&apos;utiliser leur véhicule. Ce harcèlement est insupportable pour des millions de familles qui dépendent de leur voiture dans leur vie au quotidien.</PARA><PARA>Les résultats sont là: une industrie étranglée, des citoyens accablés et une Europe hors sol, incapable de défendre ses intérêts. Il est temps de suspendre le pacte vert, de restaurer la préférence européenne et la souveraineté nationale, d&apos;exiger la réciprocité et de relocaliser nos productions stratégiques. Il est grand temps de sortir du mondialisme, de restaurer les États nations au sein d&apos;une Union européenne des coopérations. C&apos;est la seule solution d&apos;avenir pour l&apos;Europe.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="FR" INDEX="2-0075-0000" ACT="2017023910613" PRE="2017023910611" SUIV="2017023910615" VOD-START="2025-05-06T10:58:58" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:00:21"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Marion | Maréchal" PP="ECR" LG="FR" MEPID="256922" CODICT="256922"><LG>FR</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Marion Maréchal (<PP>ECR</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Monsieur le Président, certains ici semblent découvrir que les États-Unis sont un concurrent commercial féroce. Pourtant, les précédents ne manquent pas, sous l&apos;ère Biden et Obama, par exemple contre la banque BNP Paribas, qui reçut une amende considérable, ou encore le rachat forcé d&apos;Alstom et l&apos;espionnage massif révélé par Snowden.</PARA><PARA>Ceux qui ont autrefois favorisé notre dépendance militaire et économique redécouvrent aujourd&apos;hui les vertus de la souveraineté et même du protectionnisme. Ironiquement, on pourrait remercier Donald Trump pour cela. Face à cette réalité, certains proposent d&apos;aggraver encore notre déficit commercial avec la Chine. Ceci n&apos;est pas une stratégie.</PARA><PARA>Face au risque d&apos;augmentation des droits de douane, la seule réponse durable, c&apos;est un changement de modèle économique. Il n&apos;y a pas de compétitivité possible tant que notre énergie coûtera 4 à 5 fois plus qu&apos;aux États-Unis ou en Chine. Alors, plutôt que de critiquer Donald Trump, la priorité de l&apos;agenda européen devrait être la baisse du coût énergétique et donc la sortie des objectifs irréalistes du pacte vert, la relance du nucléaire, l&apos;autorisation de nouveaux forages et l&apos;investissement dans des énergies renouvelables non intermittentes comme la géothermie.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="PT" INDEX="2-0076-0000" ACT="2017023910615" PRE="2017023910613" SUIV="2017023910617" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:00:16" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:01:31"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Paulo | Do Nascimento Cabral" PP="PPE" LG="PT" MEPID="257048" CODICT="257048"><LG>PT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Paulo Do Nascimento Cabral (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Senhor Presidente, Senhor Comissário, a União Europeia e os Estados Unidos representam cerca de 30 % do comércio global, pelo que a imposição de tarifas impacta diretamente as nossas empresas e, sobretudo, os consumidores, ao refletirem-se nos preços finais, que aumentaram já cerca de 12 %.</PARA><PARA>Há três premissas que devem ser seguidas pela União Europeia.</PARA><PARA>Negociar, porque não podemos desistir do nosso aliado de sempre, e as relações transatlânticas são mais do que economia e balanças comerciais e exigem compromissos, pois assentam em valores, segurança e cooperação estratégica e transatlântica, com especial importância para o eixo Atlântico, onde Portugal e os Açores têm um papel relevante.</PARA><PARA>Incentivar novas oportunidades de diversificação de parcerias comerciais, e destaco os acordos com o Mercosul, México e África do Sul. Sempre que Trump nos fecha uma porta, a União Europeia tem de abrir uma janela.</PARA><PARA>Reforçar o nosso mercado interno, pois um estudo recente do Fundo Monetário Internacional estima que os custos das barreiras regulatórias dentro da União Europeia equivalem a tarifas de 44 % nos bens e até 110 % nos serviços. Reduzir estas barreiras mais do que mitigará o impacto das tarifas externas.</PARA><PARA>Uma posição firme e coordenada da União na defesa dos seus interesses, com autonomia estratégica e com um mercado interno robusto, é a melhor garantia perante ameaças externas, venham elas de onde vierem.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="PT" INDEX="2-0077-0000" ACT="2017023910617" PRE="2017023910615" SUIV="2017023910619" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:01:34" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:02:55"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Francisco | Assis" PP="S-D" LG="PT" MEPID="28307" CODICT="28307"><LG>PT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Francisco Assis (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Senhor Presidente, Senhor Comissário, a nova liderança americana apresenta-se com um propósito claro — destruir a ordem global assente no direito internacional e substituí-la por uma visão transacional da relação entre Estados onde, inevitavelmente, o mais forte domina e impõe.</PARA><PARA>Devemos deixar claro que o mercantilismo protecionista nunca foi e não será a solução, e que as tarifas impostas pelos Estados Unidos representam um retrocesso penalizador da economia global dos consumidores, sobretudo dos mais pobres e das empresas.</PARA><PARA>Neste contexto, a Europa deve afirmar-se como a região do livre comércio e deve reforçar os laços com parceiros que nos são mais próximos. O acordo União Europeia-Mercosul ganhou, por isso, uma importância vital, não apenas pelo seu potencial económico, mas sobretudo pela sua dimensão geoestratégica e pela afirmação de valores comuns como a democracia, o Estado de direito e os direitos humanos.</PARA><PARA>Há, contudo, um elemento essencial que não podemos perder de vista neste momento: enquanto Donald Trump e a sua administração são circunstanciais, a aliança transatlântica é duradoura e essencial. A Europa deve reagir com firmeza, mas também com inteligência e ponderação perante uma política errada e errática que prejudica, aliás, em primeiro lugar, a própria população norte-americana.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0078-0000" ACT="2017023910619" PRE="2017023910617" SUIV="2017023910621" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:02:58" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:04:06"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Alexandr | Vondra" PP="ECR" LG="EN" MEPID="197537" CODICT="197537"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Alexandr Vondra (<PP>ECR</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, the dynamism, openness and highly skilled workforce of the US economy are some of America&apos;s greatest strengths. But President Trump&apos;s tariff drive and protectionism risk undermining these very foundations.</PARA><PARA>After the Second World War, free trade helped rebuild Europe, lifting millions into prosperity and ensuring long-term peace and stability. That legacy must be defended. The European Union must champion free trade as a source of growth and resilience. We cannot afford to fall into the trap of rising protectionist sentiment. I am encouraged that the European Commission remains committed to the trade agreements. The path ahead is clear: we need more pragmatism, less green regulation and taxation, and to promote openness as much as we can.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0079-0000" ACT="2017023910621" PRE="2017023910619" SUIV="2017023910623" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:04:11" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:05:18"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Mika | Aaltola" PP="PPE" LG="EN" MEPID="256810" CODICT="256810"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Mika Aaltola (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, honourable Members, the recent tariffs imposed by the United States strike at the heart of fair and open transatlantic trade. These measures are already hurting European industries, disrupting supply chains, and shaking investor and consumer confidence.</PARA><PARA>The European Union has responded responsibly, suspending countermeasures for 90 days to allow for negotiations. But let me be clear: we shall not allow unfair treatment of our businesses or our citizens. If talks fail, we are ready to act – firmly and strategically. We have to communicate our resolve clearly: honey talking does not ultimately work with President Trump.</PARA><PARA>This is not just about economics; it&apos;s about standing up for European interests and for our collective defence. Europe is open to dialogue, but not open to intimidation.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0080-0000" ACT="2017023910623" PRE="2017023910621" SUIV="2017023910625" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:05:21" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:06:46"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Evin | Incir" PP="S-D" LG="EN" MEPID="197392" CODICT="197392"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Evin Incir (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, to US President Trump: you are a loser. Because there are no winners in this trade war; it drives up prices, destroys jobs, stifles growth and hits the most vulnerable the hardest. It affects everyday people the hardest; Trump&apos;s heavy tariffs are disturbing supply chains and, in a few weeks, shelves in the US could be empty. And it polarises a world that already is facing many challenges with, among other things, Russia&apos;s unlawful attack on Ukraine.</PARA><PARA>Trade barriers should be dismantled, not built. As the United States retreats from the global stage, turning its back on the very order it helped build after the Second World War, Europe must step up. We need an open world beyond Trump&apos;s ideology and the ideology of his extreme right-wing puppets in the EU. We need politics for the many, we need politics for the people. We must strengthen our relationship with other like-minded countries: Ukraine, Australia, Canada, Japan, India, Brazil, Mexico and many, many others. Through unity, we will ensure that today&apos;s craziness will also soon pass, and openness, cooperation and freedom will prevail.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="IT" INDEX="2-0081-0000" ACT="2017023910625" PRE="2017023910623" SUIV="2017023910627" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:06:49" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:08:11"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Francesco | Torselli" PP="ECR" LG="IT" MEPID="257163" CODICT="257163"><LG>IT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Francesco Torselli (<PP>ECR</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Signor Presidente, Signor Commissario, onorevoli colleghi, credo che la riflessione sulle relazioni commerciali fra Europa e Stati Uniti debba oggi svilupparsi su due differenti piani.</PARA><PARA>Il primo, su cui penso e spero siamo tutti d&apos;accordo, è che l&apos;Unione europea debba dare una risposta univoca alle sollecitazioni che arrivano dall&apos;altra sponda dell&apos;Atlantico.</PARA><PARA>Il secondo è che questa risposta non può essere solo il braccio di ferro, perché questo significherebbe mettere a repentaglio le nostre filiere produttive. Qualcuno in quest&apos;Aula questa mattina ha parlato di sanzioni: ci rendiamo conto, Commissario, cosa significherebbe applicare delle sanzioni? Semmai a chi?</PARA><PARA>L&apos;Europa deve pensare invece alla diversificazione dei mercati, alla tutela dei produttori, allo scambio equo delle merci.</PARA><PARA>E La lascio con una riflessione, caro Commissario: visitando aziende sul territorio, i nostri imprenditori non si dicono preoccupati soltanto per i dazi americani. Tutti ci chiedono di rivedere le folli decisioni prese in quest&apos;Aula nella scorsa legislatura, che hanno imposto alle nostre imprese costi assurdi e standard irrealizzabili.</PARA><PARA>Iniziamo col rimuovere questi dazi che l&apos;Europa ha imposto a se stessa e andremo in una direzione migliore: abbiamo grande fiducia in Lei, Commissario.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="ET" INDEX="2-0082-0000" ACT="2017023910627" PRE="2017023910625" SUIV="2017023910629" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:08:20" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:09:29"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Jüri | Ratas" PP="PPE" LG="ET" MEPID="188096" CODICT="188096"><LG>ET</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Jüri Ratas (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Austatud president! Head ametikaaslased ja volinik! Euroopa Liidu ja Ameerika Ühendriikide kaubandussuhted on aastaid olnud meie tugevuse lahutamatu osa. Eelmisel aastal ulatus kahepoolne kaubavahetus muljetavaldava kaheksasaja kuuekümne viie miljardi euroni. Meid seovad ka ühised väärtused: demokraatia, õigusriik ja turumajandus. Võimalik tollitariifide kehtestamine ähvardab lüüa mõra meie koostööle. Segadust on hetkel veel üsna palju, kuid solvumine ja emotsioonid ei tohi praegu domineerida. Euroopa peab jääma ühtseks ja kindlaks. Eesti, väikese avatud majandusega riigi esindajana ütlen selgelt: me vajame reeglitel põhinevat kaubandust, mitte suva järgi seatud tollimüüre. Samas ei saa me lubada, et meie ettevõtted ja töötajad satuvad ebaõiglase surve alla. Toetan Euroopa Komisjoni püüdlusi leida parim lahendus läbirääkimiste teel. Samal ajal peame tugevdama oma siseturgu, vähendama strateegilisi sõltuvusi ja looma uusi rahvusvahelisi partnerlussuhteid.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="RO" INDEX="2-0083-0000" ACT="2017023910629" PRE="2017023910627" SUIV="2017023910631" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:09:35" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:10:51"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Andi | Cristea" PP="S-D" LG="RO" MEPID="40224" CODICT="40224"><LG>RO</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Andi Cristea (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Domnule președinte, stimați colegi, domnule comisar, avem în față un potențial drum periculos în ceea ce privește relațiile cu prietenii noștri americani. Aveam și avem această asimetrie structurală când vine vorba de principii, valori și interese. Nu mai suntem aliniați și lucrul ăsta este profund de periculos. Aceste tarife reprezintă expresia unei crize sociale profunde în Statele Unite, o criză socială, pentru că distribuția bogăției în Statele Unite este mai inegală decât distribuția bogăției înainte de Revoluția Franceză.</PARA><PARA>Nu critic prietenii noștri americani pentru că suntem parteneri, dar prin tot ceea ce au făcut în ultimele decenii, aș spune că au prioritizat nu salariile și standardul de viață al celor care muncesc, ci au prioritizat creșterea capitalului celor care investesc, iar lucrul ăsta ar trebui să se schimbe pentru a avea liniște și un parteneriat transatlantic corespunzător.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0084-0000" ACT="2017023910631" PRE="2017023910629" SUIV="2017023910633" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:10:54" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:12:06"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Maria | Walsh" PP="PPE" LG="EN" MEPID="197863" CODICT="197863"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Maria Walsh (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, the audiovisual industry is worth over EUR 1 billion to Ireland&apos;s economy. From actor Rob Lowe to Variety magazine, the world recognises our island as a global production powerhouse.</PARA><PARA>Trump&apos;s latest threat to slap a 100 % tariff on foreign movies could wipe out our film industry in an instant. Over 16 000 jobs, many in rural Ireland, hang in the balance. A far cry from Hollywood&apos;s drama, the livelihoods of many of my constituents are in doubt as we sit here and debate this morning.</PARA><PARA>Unsurprisingly, this latest policy seems unworkable; given the international and entwined web of investors, labour and revenue, how can one even define a foreign film in this day and age? As time has taught us, there is always scope for a rollback from the Trump administration. However, while we may hope for such courage, we cannot be complacent or naive. I&apos;m calling on the Commission and our Member States to act with urgency and seek the answers from the US on the policy over the coming days and weeks.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0085-0000" ACT="2017023910633" PRE="2017023910631" SUIV="2017023910635" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:12:09" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:13:15"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Tonino | Picula" PP="S-D" LG="EN" MEPID="112744" CODICT="112744"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Tonino Picula (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, as the global order is under serious pressure, relations with our key ally are becoming one of the most important challenges we must address. It is clear that President Trump is using tariffs as a tool for blackmail. We must be prepared to respond to them equally. If he backs off, we can de-escalate, respecting our trade and digital services laws.</PARA><PARA>It&apos;s not just about the trade in goods: when we add the exchange of services to the overall trade relationship, we almost reach an equilibrium. While politics on the other side of the Atlantic is currently arbitrary and transactional, the European Union must be a factor of global stability that conducts politics clearly and in a way that is based on facts.</PARA><PARA>Moreover, this situation is an opportunity for the EU to take political responsibility, attract experts who share our values, and assume the global role because it has the democratic strength and economic capacity.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="ES" INDEX="2-0086-0000" ACT="2017023910635" PRE="2017023910633" SUIV="2017023910638" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:13:20" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:14:29"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Borja | Giménez Larraz" PP="PPE" LG="ES" MEPID="125204" CODICT="125204"><LG>ES</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Borja Giménez Larraz (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Señor presidente, la fuerza de Europa ante este desafío reside en su unión comercial. Somos un mercado decisivo a nivel global: 450 millones de personas con un alto poder adquisitivo. Tenemos el poder de hablarle de tú a tú a cualquiera –a Estados Unidos, también–.</PARA><PARA>Esta guerra comercial no beneficia a nadie; a quien la ha empezado, tampoco. Debemos hacer valer nuestra unidad. Los Estados miembros no pueden caer en la trampa de hacer la guerra por su cuenta. Nuestros rivales comerciales nos quieren divididos. Por algo será.</PARA><PARA>Negociemos hasta la extenuación con quien es nuestro principal socio comercial y aliado político, pero que sea consciente de que ante un ataque comercial tenemos herramientas y capacidad de respuesta. Y preparémosnos. Si Estados Unidos se repliega, busquemos nuevos mercados: ahí están México y Mercosur. Debemos cerrar más y mejores acuerdos.</PARA><PARA>El libre comercio es un principio fundamental del proyecto europeo: influyamos a nivel global. Frente al repliegue nacional, frente al proteccionismo y los aranceles, más libre comercio basado en reglas y más Europa.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0087-0000" ACT="2017023910638" PRE="2017023910635" SUIV="2017023910640" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:14:33" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:15:38"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Aodhán | Ó Ríordáin" PP="S-D" LG="EN" MEPID="257238" CODICT="257238"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Aodhán Ó Ríordáin (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, 80 000 Irish jobs at risk. Last week, as we marked May Day, Trump&apos;s reckless tariffs cast a shadow over workers and businesses across Europe. The full impact is unclear, but what is clear is that unless we act, it&apos;s workers who will pay the price.</PARA><PARA>We saw this in 2008, when families bore the brunt of the crash, and we can&apos;t let that happen again. We must protect those who keep our economies running: workers and small businesses. Real strength does not come from governments reneging on sick pay and living wage commitments, as the Irish Government has done, but from decent jobs, affordable housing and public investments.</PARA><PARA>These tariffs are really about a perverse perception of power, and Europe must respond with unity and resolve. If Trump wants a trade war, we won&apos;t have started it, but we won&apos;t back down. This is our moment to prove that Europe is more than a market – indeed, it is a movement – and we are a Union of values, one that stands up for its people.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0088-0000" ACT="2017023910640" PRE="2017023910638" SUIV="2017023910642" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:15:42" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:16:45"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Michał | Wawrykiewicz" PP="PPE" LG="EN" MEPID="257045" CODICT="257045"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Michał Wawrykiewicz (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, Commissioner, colleagues, the United States is again turning to protectionism – an approach history has shown to hurt, not to help, citizens. Tariffs may look like a shield, but act like a sword, raising prices and limiting choices.</PARA><PARA>Europe must not respond with isolation. Our strength is openness, competitiveness and fair trade partnerships. Instead of building walls, let&apos;s deepen ties with democratic allies, from Canada and Australia to Japan, and at the same time, maintain relations with the United States as much as economic profitability allows.</PARA><PARA>Let&apos;s not allow others&apos; short-term thinking to define our future. Free trade is not naive. It&apos;s in Europe&apos;s best interest.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0089-0000" ACT="2017023910642" PRE="2017023910640" SUIV="2017024104344" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:16:49" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:17:50"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Nina | Carberry" PP="PPE" LG="EN" MEPID="257296" CODICT="257296"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Nina Carberry (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, Commissioner, the EU and the US economic relationship is built on decades of cooperation and mutual success. However, when our industries, farmers and SMEs face unfair trade measures, Europe must respond. We are strongest when united. Acting together, we send a clear signal that we will not be divided or weakened by economic pressure.</PARA><PARA>Our response must be twofold. We must look towards our own internal market. Europe must prioritise becoming more competitive, resilient and decisive. That means investing in innovation, cutting red tape and creating a genuine market for capital.</PARA><PARA>And we must also look to new horizons, by securing new but fair trade agreements that open doors for our consumers and businesses. We have already proven that a united voice, a united Europe is the only way forward.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="IT" INDEX="2-0090-0000" ACT="2017024104344" PRE="2017023910642" SUIV="2017024104346" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:17:53" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:19:07"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Salvatore | De Meo" PP="PPE" LG="IT" MEPID="204333" CODICT="204333"><LG>IT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Salvatore De Meo (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Signor Presidente, Signor Commissario, onorevoli colleghi, le recenti tensioni commerciali con gli Stati Uniti ci ricordano quanto sia fragile l&apos;equilibrio economico globale e quanto sia necessaria, oggi più che mai, una voce europea forte, coesa e credibile.</PARA><PARA>Di fronte a delle misure unilaterali che rischiano di colpire interi settori strategici della nostra economia, la risposta dell&apos;Unione non può essere frammentata o esitante: deve basarsi sul dialogo e su una strategia chiara e condivisa. Dobbiamo rafforzare il mercato unico, rimuovere le barriere interne che ancora oggi ne limitano il suo potenziale e investire con determinazione nella nostra competitività industriale e tecnologica.</PARA><PARA>Ma il vero obiettivo deve essere più ambizioso: costruire una <EMPHAS NAME="I">partnership</EMPHAS> economica strutturata con gli Stati Uniti e con il Canada, con zero dazi, con un libero scambio equilibrato e regole comuni che tutelino imprese, lavoratori e consumatori. Non possiamo limitarci a inseguire le scelte altrui.</PARA><PARA>L&apos;Europa ha le carte in regola per essere protagonista nel commercio ma potrà farlo solo se parla con una sola voce,rafforza la propria autonomia strategica e agisce con coraggio e serietà e lungimiranza. Un&apos;Europa forte non teme il confronto ma lo guida.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="ES" INDEX="2-0091-0000" ACT="2017024104346" PRE="2017024104344" SUIV="2017024104348" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:19:10" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:20:19"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Carmen | Crespo Díaz" PP="PPE" LG="ES" MEPID="257034" CODICT="257034"><LG>ES</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Carmen Crespo Díaz (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Señor presidente, señor comisario, señores diputados, los noventa días [de suspensión de la aplicación de contramedidas] nos dan un respiro. Yo creo que la Comisión Europea lo está haciendo bien. Está siendo flexible, pero también firme.</PARA><PARA>Sabemos que la guerra comercial no beneficia a nadie, pero Estados Unidos no lo sabe a pesar de que se está resintiendo. En 2018, la situación era diferente, pero ahora disponemos de legislación que podemos aplicar. La política arancelaria tiene que tener constancia, seriedad y unión. Ni viajes inoportunos a China ni —por supuesto—, en este caso, una postura incondicional con Trump.</PARA><PARA>La unidad de acción es fundamental. La retirada de los aranceles a la soja y al gas natural es un acierto, como también lo es la retirada del bourbon y del vino. El sector agroalimentario tiene que quedar al margen porque no aguanta, no tiene colchón. Los costes de producción son elevados. Como dicen el Informe Letta y el Informe Draghi, en estos momentos tenemos que tratar la simplificación en muchos sectores, entre ellos en el agroalimentario.</PARA><PARA>Debemos garantizar la soberanía alimentaria para ser más resilientes. Sí a los acuerdos comerciales, pero evitando la competencia desleal.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0092-0000" ACT="2017024104348" PRE="2017024104346" SUIV="2017024104350" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:20:23" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:21:33"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Luděk | Niedermayer" PP="PPE" LG="EN" MEPID="124701" CODICT="124701"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Luděk Niedermayer (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, dear colleagues, US tariff policy is just wrong – not only for all the world, but also for US firms and businesses. It will be the people and firms of the US who will pay most of the hundreds of billions in tariffs if they are actually collected.</PARA><PARA>But we are not here to set the US policy. We are rightly debating our response. And here I am very glad that I can endorse the plan of the Commission, and I would just encourage the Commission to keep trying up to the last minute and find the best solution. I guess the first part of the plan is obviously an effort to minimise or avoid tariffs, and to keep or even extend the fair and free trade with the US. If you ask me if it&apos;s likely, I don&apos;t know. So that&apos;s why we should have the plan B that is proportionate.</PARA><PARA>Secondly, we should extend, where possible, trade with the third country and also coordinate on possible responses. But the most important and most effective way is to deepen and complete the single market. There is no excuse for not doing that, because it will ensure the prosperity and stability of the European economy.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="NL" INDEX="2-0093-0000" ACT="2017024104350" PRE="2017024104348" SUIV="2017024104352" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:21:36" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:23:03"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Ingeborg | Ter Laak" PP="PPE" LG="NL" MEPID="256968" CODICT="256968"><LG>NL</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Ingeborg Ter Laak (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Voorzitter, sinds de installatie van Trump zijn de termen &quot;importheffing&quot; en &quot;handelstarief&quot; nog nooit zo populair geweest. Zijn protectionisme en onvoorspelbare beleid hebben de wereldeconomie op scherp gezet. De Verenigde Staten onder Trump zijn niet langer de stabiele partner die Europa gewend was.</PARA><PARA>We moeten eerlijk zijn: Trump is onvoorspelbaar en dat zal zo blijven. Zijn tarievenpolitiek heeft geen afschrikkend effect, maar is inmiddels de standaard geworden. Waarom zouden we dan blijven hangen aan een onbetrouwbare partner? We hebben zekerheid en stabiliteit nodig. Het is aan ons, aan de politiek, om betrouwbaar en voorspelbaar te zijn. Zo niet, dan zullen bedrijven niet kunnen of willen investeren, terwijl dit juist broodnodig is voor ons concurrentievermogen en de klimaatinvesteringen.</PARA><PARA>Europa en Nederland moeten hun handelsstrategie herzien. We moeten verder kijken naar andere markten, zoals Oekraïne, India, Afrika en Zuid-Amerika. Deze regio&apos;s bieden kansen voor nieuwe handelsovereenkomsten. Dit is geen luxe, maar een noodzaak. Als we toegang willen houden tot kritische grondstoffen, als we onze welvaart op peil willen houden, dan moeten we breder denken. De toekomst van onze economie hangt niet af van één onbetrouwbare president, maar van stabiele strategische allianties wereldwijd.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="SK" INDEX="2-0094-0000" ACT="2017024104352" PRE="2017024104350" SUIV="2017024104354" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:23:07" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:24:24"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Miriam | Lexmann" PP="PPE" LG="SK" MEPID="204336" CODICT="204336"><LG>SK</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Miriam Lexmann (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Vážený pán predsedajúci, pán komisár. V týchto dňoch si pripomíname 80. výročie konca druhej svetovej vojny. Európa, ako ju poznáme, bola postavená na silnom transatlantickom zväzku a na spoločných hodnotách. Práve tie nám pomohli brániť sa proti totalitným režimom. Súčasný geopolitický kontext si vyžaduje odvážne strategické myslenie na najvyššej politickej úrovni a hľadanie udržateľnej spolupráce. Už od začiatku upozorňujem, že namiesto kritiky je potrebné konštruktívne rokovať so Spojenými štátmi a hľadať spoločné záujmy. Rozhodne by sme sa namiesto toho nemali nakláňať k nedemokratickým, totalitným režimom. Nemôžeme si dovoliť, aby dnes mali totalitné režimy príležitosť využiť naše nezhody. Flirtovanie s čínskou komunistickou stranou v konečnom dôsledku podkope našu ekonomiku, ale aj našu bezpečnosť a pošpiní dedičstvo všetkých, ktorí chránili hodnoty ľudskej dôstojnosti a demokracie, čiže základ Európskej únie.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO INDEX="2-0095-0000" ACT="2017024104354" PRE="2017024104352" SUIV="2017024104355" VL="ES"/><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">Solicitudes incidentales de uso de la palabra («catch the eye»)</EMPHAS></PARA><NUMERO VL="ES" INDEX="2-0096-0000" ACT="2017024104355" PRE="2017024104354" SUIV="2017024104357" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:24:52" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:26:16"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Francisco José | Millán Mon" PP="PPE" LG="ES" MEPID="28400" CODICT="28400"><LG>ES</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Francisco José Millán Mon (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Señor presidente, las relaciones económicas entre la Unión Europea y Estados Unidos son las más importantes del mundo.</PARA><PARA>Computemos no solo el comercio de mercancías, sino también el de servicios y las inversiones. Las cifras demuestran la gran interconexión de ambas economías en beneficio mutuo. Una guerra de aranceles no es buena ni para consumidores, ni para trabajadores, ni para empresas, ni para la economía en general. Solo fomenta la inflación.</PARA><PARA>Una economía tan boyante hasta hace meses como la de Estados Unidos registró el trimestre pasado un crecimiento negativo del 0,3 %, y es posible que entre en recesión este trimestre.</PARA><PARA>Nosotros debemos continuar la negociación en curso con Washington. La Unión Europea debe plantear una agenda positiva y ambiciosa a Estados Unidos. La agenda debe incluir el comercio y la energía, cuestiones en materia tecnológica, y abordar también los desafíos que supone el comercio con China. Se puede añadir —por qué no— la contratación pública.</PARA><PARA>Lástima no haber concluido la Asociación Transatlántica de Comercio e Inversión hace diez años, señor comisario. Qué lástima.</PARA><PARA>En paralelo, tenemos que continuar diversificando nuestras relaciones económicas y comerciales a través de acuerdos como Mercosur y México, y las negociaciones con países asiáticos como la India. No olvidemos, señor comisario, profundizar en nuestro mercado único como pidió el Informe Letta el año pasado.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="RO" INDEX="2-0097-0000" ACT="2017024104357" PRE="2017024104355" SUIV="2017024104359" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:26:31" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:27:43"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Maria | Grapini" PP="S-D" LG="RO" MEPID="124785" CODICT="124785"><LG>RO</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Maria Grapini (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Domnule președinte, domnule comisar, stimați colegi, subiectul de astăzi este extrem de important pentru viitorul Uniunii Europene. Domnule comisar, puterea de negociere este extrem de importantă din punctul de vedere al negociatorilor, dar și ce argumente au în spate. Dacă nu vom avea o piață puternică internă, nu avem cu ce să ne ducem la negociere. Dacă nu ne luăm cetățenii parteneri să creștem cumpărarea produselor europene și dezvoltarea industriei europene, nu vom avea cum să-l convingem – este libertatea de decizie a domnului Trump, oricât l-am critica.</PARA><PARA>De aceea, domnule comisar, sigur, avem un răgaz de 90 de zile, dar cu ce ne ducem la negociere? Trebuie să ne ducem cu argumente solide că da, piața Uniunii Europene este importantă, să o facem tentantă pentru Statele Unite și să reușim să negociem pe principiul câștig-câștig. Altfel, degeaba încercăm alte acorduri. E o piață consistentă. Ați spus chiar dumneavoastră, volumele mari de investiții, de schimburi comerciale, dar eu nu văd o agendă și faceți-o transparent. Spuneți-ne, cu ce argumente vă duceți acolo, la negociere?</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0098-0000" ACT="2017024104359" PRE="2017024104357" SUIV="2017024104361" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:27:51" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:28:56"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Sebastian | Tynkkynen" PP="ECR" LG="EN" MEPID="256806" CODICT="256806"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Sebastian Tynkkynen (<PP>ECR</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, our greatest adversary is not the United States, but a dictatorship far more dangerous to Europe&apos;s trade future: China.</PARA><PARA>It is quite astonishing that some in Europe have started to seek closer cooperation with the Chinese dictatorship as a response for the US. You are willing to turn a blind eye to what China presents, just to get to show your middle fingers to the other side of the Atlantic. Are you really that childish? You&apos;re all acting like a bunch of high school divas.</PARA><PARA>But I say we take a different approach. I say we grow up and work towards finding a meaningful agreement with the United States – one that benefits both parties. And we can start by cutting back on our dependence on China. Let&apos;s do that for our own sake as well, before it&apos;s too late.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="NL" INDEX="2-0099-0000" ACT="2017024104361" PRE="2017024104359" SUIV="2017024104363" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:29:01" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:30:08"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Hilde | Vautmans" PP="Renew" LG="NL" MEPID="130100" CODICT="130100"><LG>NL</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Hilde Vautmans (<PP>Renew</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Voorzitter, ik heb het debat deze ochtend gevolgd en ik zie een heel duidelijke lijn. Dit is geen technisch debat. We willen niet escaleren. Dat heb ik heel goed begrepen. Maar we willen ook niet met ons laten sollen. We moeten heel duidelijk zijn naar de &quot;bully&quot; toe.</PARA><PARA>We moeten vasthouden aan ons beste bod: een nultarief aan beide zijden. Laat president Trump ons maar aangeven wanneer hij bereid is tot onderhandelingen. Ondertussen zullen wij akkoorden sluiten met Canada, Japan en andere landen. We zullen akkoorden over handelstarieven sluiten waar beide partijen beter van worden, niet slechter. Ik denk dat dit de lijn moet zijn.</PARA><PARA>Europa is tot veel bereid, maar we zijn geen dommeriken: we willen onze burgers en bedrijven beschermen.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="ES" INDEX="2-0100-0000" ACT="2017024104363" PRE="2017024104361" SUIV="2017024104365" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:30:18" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:31:32"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Jaume | Asens Llodrà" PP="Verts/ALE" LG="ES" MEPID="257015" CODICT="257015"><LG>ES</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Jaume Asens Llodrà (<PP>Verts/ALE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Señor presidente, la guerra comercial de Trump es un síntoma de una crisis estructural, la del orden neoliberal que ha gobernado desde los años 80 el comercio global. Toda crisis es una oportunidad, no para volver a lo de antes o para imitar a Trump en una dinámica autodestructiva, sino para repensar el modelo desde parámetros más justos.</PARA><PARA>Eso significa muchas cosas, pero —entre otras— fortalecer la soberanía democrática de nuestra economía, condicionar las importaciones al respeto de los estándares laborales y medioambientales. Significa también crear un espacio digital propio europeo, apostar por una multilateralidad más equilibrada y condicionar —impulsar— un control público de los sectores económicos estratégicos.</PARA><PARA>Frente a los muros que levanta Trump, Europa debe levantar derechos. No debemos combatir el neoproteccionismo de Estados Unidos al servicio de las élites locales con más neoliberalismo al servicio de las élites globales. Por eso, otro mundo y otro comercio son posibles y urgentes.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0101-0000" ACT="2017024104365" PRE="2017024104363" SUIV="2017024104367" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:31:38" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:32:54"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Marc | Botenga" PP="The Left" LG="EN" MEPID="187917" CODICT="187917"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Marc Botenga (<PP>The Left</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, Commissioner Šefčovič, I read your remarks in the press and I sometimes wonder: is there a Eurovision contest for being Washington&apos;s best lapdog? Because, honestly, Trump threatens us and your reaction is: well, we might import more shale gas. Yes, that&apos;s going to cost us very, very dearly, our workers will pay more, it&apos;s going to pollute our planet, but we&apos;ll do it. Please be nice to us!&apos;</PARA><PARA>The agricultural produce: I think you spoke about more beans on the EU market. Why do we want to reward him, or China? You say, &apos;yes, let&apos;s be tougher on China&apos;. This will mean increased prices for European consumers and less access potentially to technology for our economy.</PARA><PARA>I think if you really want to react to what Trump is doing – and what you would do if you were attacked by, I don&apos;t know, China with a trade war, or Russia or whatever – you would invest in our own infrastructure. Why don&apos;t we take, I don&apos;t know, public energy companies? They can guarantee cheap, affordable energy to industries and to workers. Or diversify our relations also with China and with all these other countries that have been mentioned? That is the strategy and that is what we need.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EL" INDEX="2-0102-0000" ACT="2017024104367" PRE="2017024104365" SUIV="2017024104369" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:33:00" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:34:05"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Κώστας | Παπαδάκης" PP="NI" LG="EL" MEPID="125093" CODICT="125093"><LG>EL</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Κώστας Παπαδάκης (<PP>NI</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η επιβολή δασμών από τις Ηνωμένες Πολιτείες, η ανταλλαγή δασμών και αντίμετρων μεταξύ Ηνωμένων Πολιτειών και Κίνας αποτελούν τμήμα του ανταγωνισμού τους για την πρωτοκαθεδρία στο διεθνές καπιταλιστικό σύστημα, στο οποίο η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση και η Ρωσία εκπληρώνουν τον δικό τους ρόλο υπέρ των μονοπωλίων.</PARA><PARA>Εμπορικοί πόλεμοι, κυνήγι σπάνιων γαιών, πηγών και δρόμων μεταφοράς ενέργειας και εμπορευμάτων συνδέονται άρρηκτα με τις αιτίες των πολέμων, ενώ τεράστια κεφάλαια συσσωρεύονται προετοιμάζοντας το έδαφος για νέα οικονομική κρίση του συστήματος εκμετάλλευσης. Οι λαοί της Ευρώπης δεν έχουν κανένα συμφέρον να στρατευτούν με τους πολεμικούς και εμπορικούς σχεδιασμούς της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης, ούτε με τους ανταγωνιστές της.</PARA><PARA>Το μόνο σίγουρο είναι ότι ο βαρύς λογαριασμός πολέμων, δασμών και κυρώσεων θα φορτωθεί στους λαούς. Για αυτό πρέπει, χαράζοντας αυτοτελή δρόμο, να απαιτήσουν να μη γίνει καμία θυσία για τα κέρδη και τους ανταγωνισμούς, σηκώνοντας ψηλά τη σημαία των διεκδικήσεων, των σύγχρονων αναγκών και δικαιωμάτων. Στην πράξη αποδεικνύεται ότι, για να κερδίσει ο εργαζόμενος λαός, πρέπει να χάσει το μεγάλο κεφάλαιο.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="RO" INDEX="2-0103-0000" ACT="2017024104369" PRE="2017024104367" SUIV="2017024104371" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:34:14" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:35:34"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Diana | Iovanovici Şoşoacă" PP="NI" LG="RO" MEPID="257120" CODICT="257120"><LG>RO</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Diana Iovanovici Şoşoacă (<PP>NI</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Domnule președinte, nu știu cum credeți dumneavoastră că negociați cu cineva pe care l-ați jignit înainte să fie ales și după ce a fost ales. Nu știu de ce nu vă invită nimeni. Pe mine m-au invitat republicanii și administrația prezidențială și la Washington CPAC, și acum trei săptămâni, la Mar-a-Lago, și vă spun că am vorbit direct cu ei. Se poate vorbi, dar discutăm aici despre economie. Dumneavoastră când angajați oameni sau îi puneți pe listă, îi întrebați care sunt opțiunile lor sexuale în loc să întrebați care sunt opțiunile lor economice și ce pregătire au.</PARA><PARA>Cu tot respectul, dar dumneavoastră distrugeți Europa. Trump își apără cetățenii săi și țara sa. Dumneavoastră ați distrus Europa. Vorbiți de dictatură în Statele Unite ale Americii? Voi, socialiștii, ați fost acolo? Păi, mai dictatură ca în Europa nu cred că e nici în Coreea de Nord și ați distrus democrația din România, unde ați intervenit în alegerile noastre, de avem alegeri fraudate, ilegale, neconstituționale și ați interzis candidați în frunte cu mine! Asta ar trebui să vă gândiți, cum să faceți Europa să fie democratică și România mare din nou!</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="PT" INDEX="2-0104-0000" ACT="2017024104371" PRE="2017024104369" SUIV="2017024104373" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:35:44" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:37:00"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="João | Oliveira" PP="The Left" LG="PT" MEPID="257083" CODICT="257083"><LG>PT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">João Oliveira (<PP>The Left</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Senhor Presidente, Senhor Comissário Šefčovič, a resposta à política de tarifas de Trump tem de assentar em três elementos essenciais.</PARA><PARA>Primeiro, o reforço do mercado interno com o aumento do poder de compra, apoiando políticas de aumento de salários e de pensões. Reforçando o nosso mercado interno, temos uma economia menos dependente, menos vulnerável, menos exposta às decisões que outros tomam, sobretudo quando elas nos são prejudiciais.</PARA><PARA>Em segundo lugar, precisamos de desenvolver as nossas capacidades produtivas, particularmente com uma política de reindustrialização e de incorporação de ciência e tecnologia na produção das nossas empresas para garantir que, também assim, ficamos menos vulneráveis e menos dependentes das decisões de política económica e comercial que outros tomam, nomeadamente quando decidem aumentar tarifas não apenas sobre bens, mas também sobre matérias-primas.</PARA><PARA>Em terceiro lugar, é absolutamente essencial termos uma política comercial diversificada, com acordos de comércio que não sacrifiquem as economias e os interesses dos pequenos países face aos interesses das grandes potências e que, sobretudo, permitam encontrar formas adequadas de desenvolvimento económico na base de relações internacionais de cooperação.</PARA><PARA>Esse é o caminho que deve ser seguido, não o da subserviência aos Estados Unidos e à administração de Trump.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="PT" INDEX="2-0105-0000" ACT="2017024104373" PRE="2017024104371" SUIV="2017024104375" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:37:06" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:38:12"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Ana | Miranda Paz" PP="Verts/ALE" LG="PT" MEPID="24942" CODICT="24942"><LG>PT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Ana Miranda Paz (<PP>Verts/ALE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Senhor Presidente, a pausa do medo, a chantagem e os delírios do senhor Trump não podem ser o motor para a nossa política comercial europeia. Não podemos ceder à chantagem desse líder autoritário. É necessário avaliar imediatamente o impacto das taxas impostas por Trump: ameaça direta à soberania dos nossos povos, ameaça à economia e ao emprego e ameaça ao direito internacional.</PARA><PARA>No meu país, a Galiza, a política intervencionista do senhor Trump ameaça o setor metalúrgico e do vinho, o setor automóvel e também outros setores.</PARA><PARA>Precisamos, Senhor Comissário, de investimentos nesses setores estratégicos. Também precisamos de independência estratégica. E também, Senhor Comissário, de capacidade produtiva e de proteger a nossa indústria para evitar o <EMPHAS NAME="I">dumping</EMPHAS> no emprego e o <EMPHAS NAME="I">dumping</EMPHAS> social e económico.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="ES" INDEX="2-0106-0000" ACT="2017024104375" PRE="2017024104373" SUIV="2017024104377" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:38:20" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:39:22"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Juan Fernando | López Aguilar" PP="S-D" LG="ES" MEPID="96812" CODICT="96812"><LG>ES</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Juan Fernando López Aguilar (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Señor presidente, comisario Šefčovič, es evidente que el regreso de Trump a la Casa Blanca ha significado una patada al tablero del desorden global y que la disyuntiva está despejada en este debate. No cabe ni adelantarse ni desbaratarse, solo cabe una reacción unitaria de defensa de un mundo basada en reglas y en el multilateralismo, también en el comercio global.</PARA><PARA>Pero hay un mensaje que no ha emergido todavía y en el que tenemos que ser especialmente unánimes, y es en decirle a Trump: «<EMPHAS NAME="I">the EU was not meant to screw the US».</EMPHAS> En ningún caso la Unión Europea se hizo para fastidiar a Estados Unidos. La idea europea es endógena. La idea europea tiene valor en sí misma y la Unión Europea tiene que afirmarse con autonomía: autonomía estratégica y también autonomía frente a esas medidas unilaterales ante las que solo cabe oponer contramedidas justas y proporcionadas, pero, sobre todo, afirmando la autonomía y la razón de ser de la Unión Europea.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="IT" INDEX="2-0107-0000" ACT="2017024104377" PRE="2017024104375" SUIV="2017024104379" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:39:30" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:40:57"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Lucia | Annunziata" PP="S-D" LG="IT" MEPID="257123" CODICT="257123"><LG>IT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Lucia Annunziata (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Signor Presidente, Signor Commissario, onorevoli colleghi, parlerò in italiano. Lei mi perdonerà se non parlo di dazi ma di Gaza. Queste due vicende in realtà rispondono alla stessa idea di politica: la sostituzione da parte di Trump dell&apos;interesse pubblico con quello privato.</PARA><PARA>Tutti sappiamo che tra sei giorni il presidente Trump sarà a Gerusalemme nella sua prima visita internazionale. E Bibi Netanyahu, il suo governo, ha pensato di presentargli in quella situazione un regalo. Sappiamo dal piano che è stato approvato ieri che il governo intende invadere Gaza per spostare i palestinesi dal loro territorio e intende poi affidare il loro benessere solo alle organizzazioni di beneficenza private.</PARA><PARA>Questo significa una cosa molto importante: significa l&apos;abolizione di un&apos;altra pagina della nostra democrazia, che è stata fatta di società di intermediazioni, di una politica di intermediazione. Fuori saranno dunque le organizzazioni umanitarie, quelle degli Stati, la stessa ONU in definitiva, ma anche le nostre.</PARA><PARA>Io guardo a questo anno che sono stata qui e non ho notato altro che l&apos;incapacità di fare differenza in Palestina. Ma non preoccupatevi: i fantasmi dei fallimenti stanno sempre alle nostre porte.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0108-0000" ACT="2017024104379" PRE="2017024104377" SUIV="2017024104381" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:41:00" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:42:06"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Vytenis Povilas | Andriukaitis" PP="S-D" LG="EN" MEPID="119652" CODICT="119652"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Vytenis Povilas Andriukaitis (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Mr President, dear Commissioner, dear Maroš, I welcome your statement today. The predictable unpredictability of Trump&apos;s policies is a challenge, and Trump&apos;s brutal tariff war and nationalist protectionism are a real threat. We must stay united and determined in promoting and defending rule‑based global trade and multilateralism, and, of course, we need to intensify trade with other markets like Mercosur, and modernise and capitalise on the benefits of existing free trade agreements, as with Canada and Mexico.</PARA><PARA>But we must also urgently complete our single market, urgently provide EU‑wide targeted support for impacted European industries and our affected regions. State aid to our industries and small and medium-sized enterprises is necessary. We must buy European goods and services and promote Made in Europe products. Our strategic, industrial and autonomy demands it.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="PL" INDEX="2-0109-0000" ACT="2017024104381" PRE="2017024104379" SUIV="2017024104384" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:42:13" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:43:23"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Dariusz | Joński" PP="PPE" LG="PL" MEPID="257031" CODICT="257031"><LG>PL</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Dariusz Joński (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Panie Przewodniczący! Panie Komisarzu! Wartość ceł nakładanych przez Stany Zjednoczone na unijny eksport to wzrost z 7 mld euro w 2023 r. do 81 mld euro w 2025 r. To jest prawie 74 mld euro więcej. Około 70% produktów unijnych eksportowanych do Stanów będzie podlegać dodatkowej opłacie.</PARA><PARA>Oczywiście najbardziej dotknięty zostanie sektor motoryzacyjny. Unijny eksport wart mniej więcej 66 mld euro zostanie obłożony w kwocie 16,5 miliarda euro dodatkowymi opłatami. To również dotyczy mojego kraju, bo produkujemy 800 tysięcy samochodów, a w tym sektorze pracuje 200 tysięcy osób.</PARA><PARA>Mówiąc wprost, globalna gospodarka może stracić nawet 7% PKB. To równowartość gospodarek Niemiec i Francji razem wziętych. Unia Europejska nie chce wojny celnej, ale chce partnerstwa. Dlatego ta propozycja zerowych ceł w dwie strony jest bardzo rozsądną i oczekiwaną – myślę, że z dwóch stron - propozycją.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO INDEX="2-0110-0000" ACT="2017024104384" PRE="2017024104381" SUIV="2017024104383" VL="ES"/><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(Fin de las intervenciones con arreglo al procedimiento de solicitud incidental de uso de la palabra («catch the eye»))</EMPHAS></PARA><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0111-0000" ACT="2017024104383" PRE="2017024104384" SUIV="2017024104386" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:43:32" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:50:45"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Maroš | Šefčovič" PP="NULL" LG="EN" MEPID="0" CODICT="99424" SPEAKER_TYPE="membre de la Commission"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Maroš Šefčovič, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">Member of the Commission</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Mr President, honourable Minister, honourable Members of the European Parliament, first and foremost, Mr President, I would like to thank you for organising the work of this House in a way that we can have regular debates on issues of strategic importance. Yesterday we had an excellent debate on the future relationship with the United Kingdom. Today we are discussing how we should advance our negotiations and relationship with the United States of America.</PARA><PARA>I see that Chairman Lange is here. I also would like to appreciate the almost-permanent interaction with the INTA Committee and with all relevant committees, because clearly this is such an important issue that we have to act united, we have to work together and we have to be properly informed. We always seek, of course, the input and guidance from the European Parliament in these very important issues.</PARA><PARA>Today&apos;s debate was one of the most profound, and also one of the longest, which just reflects the importance of the topic we are discussing. I really would like to thank all of you, because the overall impression I&apos;ve got is that we understand each other very much on how to pursue what I would describe as a four-pillar policy.</PARA><PARA>The first one – Mr Warborn mentioned it, but also a lot of other colleagues, Mr Procaccini, Mr Kols, Ms Vedrenne – that we should use every opportunity to engage with our American partners to negotiate and to look for fair and – I would underline – balanced solutions. As you can imagine, it&apos;s not easy. But I can also reassure you that we will do our utmost to arrive at that destination, because we, as the biggest trading partner of the United States of America, with millions of jobs to be affected by these measures on both sides of the Atlantic, feel responsibility for making sure that we find the best possible solution for both of us.</PARA><PARA>Many of you proposed ideas which, frankly, we already tested. We proposed and we are waiting for the reaction from our American partners. For example, zero-zero tariffs for cars, but also for industrial goods, looking at what we can do in different certification processes to make sure that we make it easier for our businesses, and not more complicated, for them to actually profit from this biggest, most massive trade relationship on this planet.</PARA><PARA>I was personally discussing with the Secretary of Commerce, Mr Lutnick, and Mr Jamieson Greer, who is leading the USTR offices, on multiple occasions, and we spent together dozens and dozens of hours on where we would be much stronger if we would act together. Let&apos;s tackle the dependencies, if it comes to critical raw materials, if it comes to key supply materials for our medicines. Let&apos;s tackle together overcapacity in the steel sector, because these are the areas where we can clearly achieve much more together if we work as allies, as partners. So let&apos;s see what would be the reaction from our American partners.</PARA><PARA>At the same time, I would like to reassure everyone, especially Mr López Aguilar, that we do not feel weak. We do not feel under undue pressure to accept the deal which would not be fair for us. We are absolutely clear that we are the biggest trading bloc on this planet, with a very strong economy and with the biggest network of free trade agreements.</PARA><PARA>We know that these negotiations might not, in the end, succeed, in spite of all our sincere efforts. So therefore we, of course, are preparing for the possible – and it might be needed – rebalancing. As you&apos;ve been informed about our first set of measures, which we suspended because we wanted to create space for negotiations, so we will be continuing our preparation for further rebalancing if needed. I would like to reassure all of you that all options are clearly on the table.</PARA><PARA>The third very important element raised by many of you is that we have to highlight that these tariffs are simply unjust, unfair and in total breach of international commercial law. Therefore we are also considering other options and to challenge these measures in the WTO. So we are fully aware how important this is. All the trading world is looking at making sure that we will come back to the rules-based international trade, to respect of the rules for all of us, because this is how international trade should function in the future.</PARA><PARA>The last point – and thank you very much to those who mentioned it so clearly, Ms Van Brempt, Ms Hahn, Ms Niebler – and I appreciate also the support from Mr Oliveira – who were highlighting the importance of diversifying our trade relations.</PARA><PARA>We have to make sure that we would get the most out of 87 % of global trade. I can tell you that our phones are not stopping ringing all the time, because everyone wants to accelerate free trade agreements, negotiations with us. Everyone wants to open them if they are not open, and we are clearly opening more avenues.</PARA><PARA>I am sure that after this mandate, the European Commission will have much larger free trade networks than it has right now, and it will be clearly to the benefit of our workers, of our businesses, of our SMEs, because we are going to open access for the new markets and we are going to promote the European, fair, sustainable way of trading.</PARA><PARA>If you allow me on the last point, Mr President, I totally agree with you that we need not only to look abroad, but also to look at what we can do better inside of our European Union. This particular situation with the tariffs is highlighting that also on our internal market, we still have too many barriers which are limiting the potential of our single market, which are making it difficult for our businesses, especially for our SMEs, to thrive even more on the single market.</PARA><PARA>Therefore, Executive Vice-President Mr Séjourné was clearly tasked by our President, Ursula von der Leyen, to focus on this like a laser beam – to remove the tariffs, to increase the potential of the single market – because that&apos;s a very strong response. This is where we could be much more forceful than in the past.</PARA><PARA>I believe that the combination of all these measures would make sure that Europe will not only remain the biggest trader on this planet, but also the strongest economy we have, and in close cooperation with the partners who share the same ideals, the same principles, when it comes to international trading.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0112-0000" ACT="2017024104386" PRE="2017024104383" SUIV="2017024104387" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:50:51" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:03"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Adam | Szłapka" PP="NULL" LG="EN" MEPID="0" CODICT="264609" SPEAKER_TYPE="président en exercice du Conseil"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Adam Szłapka, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">President-in-Office of the Council</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Mr President, Mr Commissioner, honourable Members, thank you very much for this debate. Despite current difficulties, the US is our strategic partner and ally, and our trade and investment relationship remains of key importance. The sheer unpredictability of the current trade and investment environment is detrimental to both the EU and the US, as well as globally. We therefore remain committed to engaging and finding a fair and mutually balanced negotiated solution. At the same time, we need to focus on ourselves, on what more we can do to help our industry to enhance competitiveness and spur economic growth in the EU.</PARA><PARA>The unity has characterised our approach so far, and I believe it will remain our key asset also in the future. Under any scenario, we are determined to promote our common interests and defend our legitimate rights. Together, in a spirit of unity, we shall achieve our goals.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="EN" INDEX="2-0113-0000" ACT="2017024104387" PRE="2017024104386" SUIV="2017024733299" VOD-START="2025-05-06T11:52:02" VOD-END="2025-05-06T11:52:07"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="President" PP="NULL" LG="EN" MEPID="125027" CODICT="125027"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">President.</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – The debate is closed.</PARA></INTERVENTION><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="B"><EMPHAS NAME="I">Declaraciones por escrito (artículo 178 del Reglamento interno)</EMPHAS></EMPHAS></PARA><NUMERO VL="ES" INDEX="2-0113-1250" ACT="2017025491417" PRE="2017024733299" SUIV="2017025491348"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Lina | Gálvez" PP="S-D" LG="ES" MEPID="197702" CODICT="197702"><LG>ES</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Lina Gálvez (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>), </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">por escrito</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – En materia de comercio este es el asunto que más está preocupando a la UE y a las instituciones multilaterales: los efectos sobre la economía y sobre el orden político y económico mundial de las líneas políticas y en este caso, comerciales, de la nueva administración norteamericana.</PARA><PARA>Unidad es el concepto que se destaca por encima de los demás. El Presidente de los Estados Unidos no debe conseguir dividirnos a los miembros de la UE y despreciar a las instituciones de la Unión.</PARA><PARA>La inmediata reacción del Gobierno de España, coordinada con la UE, al poner en marcha el Plan de apoyo a las empresas ante los efectos de los aranceles, señala una de las vías de enfrentar esta situación: apoyo al tejido productivo y comercial, y a la ciudadanía.</PARA><PARA>Nuestro Grupo S&amp;D, ha lamentado las medidas ilegales de los Estados Unidos y avisa de que anunciaban un panorama de inflación y riesgo para miles de empleos.</PARA><PARA>Las y los socialistas estamos a favor de una solución negociada, pero también de una respuesta con determinación, rapidez, proporcionalidad y unidad.</PARA><PARA>Estamos a favor del multilateralismo frente al unilateralismo que defiende EEUU; un mundo basado en reglas frente a decisiones unilaterales fuera del orden de cooperación comercial establecido y acordado.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="ES" INDEX="2-0113-2500" ACT="2017025491348" PRE="2017025491417" SUIV="2017025812955"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Nicolás | González Casares" PP="S-D" LG="ES" MEPID="197718" CODICT="197718"><LG>ES</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Nicolás González Casares (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>), </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">por escrito</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – En materia de comercio, este es el asunto que más está preocupando a la UE y a las instituciones multilaterales: los efectos sobre la economía y sobre el orden político y económico mundial de las líneas políticas y, en este caso, comerciales de la nueva administración norteamericana.</PARA><PARA/><PARA>Unidad es el concepto que se destaca por encima de los demás. El presidente de los Estados Unidos no debe conseguir dividirnos a los miembros de la UE y despreciar a las instituciones de la Unión.</PARA><PARA/><PARA>La inmediata reacción del Gobierno de España, coordinada con la UE, al poner en marcha el Plan de apoyo a las empresas ante los efectos de los aranceles señala una de las vías de enfrentar esta situación: apoyo al tejido productivo y comercial y a los ciudadanos.</PARA><PARA/><PARA>Nuestro Grupo S&amp;D ha lamentado las medidas ilegales por parte de los Estados Unidos y avisa de que anunciaban un panorama de inflación y riesgo para miles de empleos.</PARA><PARA/><PARA>Los socialistas estamos a favor de una solución negociada, pero también de una respuesta con determinación, rapidez, proporcionalidad y unidad.</PARA><PARA/><PARA>Estamos a favor del multilateralismo frente al unilateralismo que defiende EEUU; un mundo basado en reglas frente a decisiones unilaterales fuera del orden de cooperación comercial establecido y acordado.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="ES" INDEX="2-0113-3125" ACT="2017025812955" PRE="2017025491348" SUIV="2017025491349"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Javi | López" PP="S-D" LG="ES" MEPID="125042" CODICT="125042"><LG>ES</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Javi López (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>), </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">por escrito</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – En materia de comercio este es el asunto que más está preocupando a la UE y a las instituciones multilaterales: los efectos sobre la economía y sobre el orden político y económico mundial de las líneas políticas y en este caso, comerciales, de la nueva administración norteamericana.</PARA><PARA>Unidad es el concepto que se destaca por encima de los demás. El Presidente de los Estados Unidos no debe conseguir dividirnos a los miembros de la UE y despreciar a las instituciones de la Unión.</PARA><PARA>La inmediata reacción del Gobierno de España, coordinada con la UE, al poner en marcha el Plan de apoyo a las empresas ante los efectos de los aranceles señala una de las vías de enfrentar esta situación: apoyo al tejido productivo y comercial, y a los ciudadanos.</PARA><PARA>Nuestro Grupo S&amp;D, ha lamentado las medidas ilegales por parte de los Estados Unidos y avisa de que anunciaban un panorama de inflación y riesgo para miles de empleos.</PARA><PARA>Los socialistas estamos a favor de una solución negociada, pero también de una respuesta con determinación, rapidez, proporcionalidad y unidad.</PARA><PARA>Estamos a favor del multilateralismo frente al unilateralismo que defiende EEUU; un mundo basado en reglas frente a decisiones unilaterales fuera del orden de cooperación comercial establecido y acordado.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="ES" INDEX="2-0113-3750" ACT="2017025491349" PRE="2017025812955" SUIV="2017025812956"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="César | Luena" PP="S-D" LG="ES" MEPID="197721" CODICT="197721"><LG>ES</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">César Luena (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>), </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">por escrito</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – En materia de comercio este es el asunto que más está preocupando a la UE y a las instituciones multilaterales: los efectos sobre la economía y sobre el orden político y económico mundial de las líneas políticas y en este caso, comerciales, de la nueva administración norteamericana.</PARA><PARA>Unidad es el concepto que se destaca por encima de los demás. El Presidente de los Estados Unidos no debe conseguir dividirnos a los miembros de la UE y despreciar a las instituciones de la Unión.</PARA><PARA>La inmediata reacción del Gobierno de España, coordinada con la UE, al poner en marcha el Plan de apoyo a las empresas ante los efectos de los aranceles señala una de las vías de enfrentar esta situación: apoyo al tejido productivo y comercial, y a los ciudadanos.</PARA><PARA>Nuestro Grupo S&amp;D, ha lamentado las medidas ilegales por parte de los Estados Unidos y avisa de que anunciaban un panorama de inflación y riesgo para miles de empleos.</PARA><PARA>Los socialistas estamos a favor de una solución negociada, pero también de una respuesta con determinación, rapidez, proporcionalidad y unidad.</PARA><PARA>Estamos a favor del multilateralismo frente al unilateralismo que defiende EEUU; un mundo basado en reglas frente a decisiones unilaterales fuera del orden de cooperación comercial establecido y acordado.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="ES" INDEX="2-0113-4375" ACT="2017025812956" PRE="2017025491349" SUIV="2017024733306"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Cristina | Maestre" PP="S-D" LG="ES" MEPID="197719" CODICT="197719"><LG>ES</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Cristina Maestre (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>), </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">por escrito</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – En materia de comercio este es el asunto que más está preocupando a la UE y a las instituciones multilaterales: los efectos sobre la economía y sobre el orden político y económico mundial de las líneas políticas y en este caso, comerciales, de la nueva administración norteamericana.</PARA><PARA>Unidad es el concepto que se destaca por encima de los demás. El Presidente de los Estados Unidos no debe conseguir dividirnos a los miembros de la UE y despreciar a las instituciones de la Unión.</PARA><PARA>La inmediata reacción del Gobierno de España, coordinada con la UE, al poner en marcha el Plan de apoyo a las empresas ante los efectos de los aranceles señala una de las vías de enfrentar esta situación: apoyo al tejido productivo y comercial, y a los ciudadanos.</PARA><PARA>Nuestro Grupo S&amp;D, ha lamentado las medidas ilegales por parte de los Estados Unidos y avisa de que anunciaban un panorama de inflación y riesgo para miles de empleos.</PARA><PARA>Los socialistas estamos a favor de una solución negociada, pero también de una respuesta con determinación, rapidez, proporcionalidad y unidad.</PARA><PARA>Estamos a favor del multilateralismo frente al unilateralismo que defiende EEUU; un mundo basado en reglas frente a decisiones unilaterales fuera del orden de cooperación comercial establecido y acordado.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO VL="RO" INDEX="2-0113-5000" ACT="2017024733306" PRE="2017025812956" SUIV="2017024104388"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR LIB="Iuliu | Winkler" PP="PPE" LG="RO" MEPID="39725" CODICT="39725"><LG>RO</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Iuliu Winkler (<PP>PPE</PP>), </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">în scris</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Sistemul economic global este zguduit din temelii, iar viitorul este extrem de greu de întrevăzut mai ales din cauza imprevizibilității de care dă dovadă Washingtonul. Nu este pentru prima dată când europenii se află sub spectrul războiului comercial. Este însă pentru prima oară când consecințele acestuia sunt extrem de profunde și ample pentru că trăim în plină eră a globalizării cu lanțuri de aprovizionare strâns legate. Avem un respiro de trei luni în care trebuie să fim înțelepți, determinați și decisivi în negocierile cu SUA. În noile condiții, este esențial ca să ne păstrăm calmul și să le reamintim tuturor partenerilor că UE este de încredere și predictibilă. Comerțul este o competență exclusivă a Uniunii și doar păstrând unitatea, negociatorii noștri pot să se bazeze pe puterea pieței unice și a celor 450 de milioane de cetățeni europeni. UE are nevoie, mai mult ca niciodată de diversificarea relațiilor comerciale, fiind important să finalizăm negocierile aflate în curs cu state din Asia de Sud-Est, cu Australia sau India. Păstrând aceste priorități și mergând pe drumul marcat de interesele, dar și de valorile noastre europene, vom reuși să rămânem punctul de stabilitate în mijlocul unei economii globale extrem de turbulente.</PARA></INTERVENTION></CHAPTER>